<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" containing-doc="Pueblo of Picuris Tribal Law and Order Code">
  <prefix>Title</prefix>
  <num>4</num>
  <heading>Criminal Justice</heading>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>4.01</num>
    <heading>General and Preliminary Matters</heading>
    <section>
      <num>4.01.010</num>
      <heading>Name of Citation.</heading>
      <text><cite path="4">This title</cite> shall be known and may be cited as the "Pueblo of Picuris Criminal Code," and references in <cite path="4">this title</cite> to "Code" shall refer to this Code unless another is clearly indicated.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.01.010 was formerly codified as 4-1-1</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.01.020</num>
      <heading>Effective Date.</heading>
      <text>This Code shall apply to all offenses as herein defined occurring on or after its effective date of June 16, 2008. If all or any part of any offense was committed prior to such date, the offense shall be governed by the prior existing law except that defenses enumerated herein shall apply to all offenses tried after the effective date.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.01.020 was formerly codified as 4-1-2</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.01.030</num>
      <heading>Purpose and Construction.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The provisions of this Code shall be construed in accordance with these general principles and purposes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>To forbid and prevent the commission of offenses and give fair warning of conduct, which is declared to be an offense;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>To define adequately the conduct and mental state which constitute each offense and safeguard conduct that is without fault from condemnation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>To prescribe penalties which are proportionate to the seriousness of the offense and which permit recognition of differing rehabilitative needs of individual offenders while at the same time recognizing the need of society to protect itself, when necessary, from offenders;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>To prevent arbitrary and oppressive treatment of persons accused or convicted of offenses and to promote the correction and rehabilitation of such persons.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>This Code shall not be strictly construed, but shall be construed according to the fair import of the terms used to promote fairness and justice and accomplish the general purposes set forth herein.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.01.030 was formerly codified as 4-1-3</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.01.040</num>
      <heading>Exclusiveness of Offenses.</heading>
      <text>No conduct constitutes an offense unless so declared by this Code, or by any other provisions of this Tribal Code, or by any other Tribal resolution or ordinance or by federal law.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.01.040 was formerly codified as 4-1-4</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.01.050</num>
      <heading>Civil Liability Unaffected.</heading>
      <text>This Code does not change, suspend or otherwise affect any civil or other liability, other than criminal liability as defined herein, which would otherwise arise from any conduct defined herein.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.01.050 was formerly codified as 4-1-5</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.01.060</num>
      <heading>Prosecution for Multiple Offenses.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>When the same conduct of a defendant may establish the commission of more than one offense, the defendant may be prosecuted for each such offense. He/she may not, however, be convicted of more than one offense if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>One offense is included in the other; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>One offense consists only of a conspiracy, solicitation, or an attempt to commit the other; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Inconsistent findings of fact are required to establish the offenses; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>The offenses only differ in that one is defined to prohibit a specific kind of conduct and the other prohibits the same conduct generally; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>The offense is defined, as a continuing course of conduct and the defendant's course of conduct were uninterrupted, unless the Code provides that specific periods of such conduct constitute separate offenses.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.01.060 was formerly codified as 4-1-6</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.01.070</num>
      <heading>Limitation.</heading>
      <text>Except as provided in <cite path="§4.01.080">Section 4.01.080</cite> below, a defendant shall not be subject to separate trials for multiple offenses based on the same conduct or arising from the same criminal episode, if such offenses are known to the prosecuting officer at the time of the commencement of the first trial and are within the jurisdiction of the Pueblo of Picuris Tribal Court.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.01.070 was formerly codified as 4-1-7</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.01.080</num>
      <heading>Included Offenses</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A defendant may be convicted of an offense included in an offense charged in the complaint without having been specifically charged with such included offense. An offense is so included when:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>It is established by proof of the same or less than all the facts required to establish the commission of the offense charged; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>It consists of an attempt or conspiracy to commit the offense charged or to commit an offense otherwise included therein; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>It differs from the offense charged only in the respect that a less serious injury or risk of injury to the same person, property or public interest or a lesser kind of culpability suffices to establish its commission.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Court need not charge the jury with respect to an included offense unless there is a rational basis for a verdict acquitting the defendant of the offense charged and convicting him/her of the included offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.01.080 was formerly codified as 4-1-8</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.01.090</num>
      <heading>Double Jeopardy.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>If a defendant has been prosecuted for one or more offenses arising out of a single criminal episode or the same facts as the original prosecution, a subsequent prosecution for the same or a different offense arising out of such episode or facts is barred if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The subsequent prosecution is for an offense that was or should have been tried under this Code in the former prosecution, unless such subsequent trial has been ordered as a separate trial by the Judge; and the former:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Resulted in acquittal; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Resulted in conviction; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>Was improperly terminated; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(D)</num>
            <text>Was terminated by a final order of judgment for the defendant that has not been reversed, set aside or vacated and that necessarily required a determination inconsistent with a fact that must be established to secure conviction in the subsequent prosecution.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>There is an acquittal if the prosecution resulted in a finding of not guilty by the trier of facts or in a determination that there was insufficient evidence to warrant conviction. A finding of guilty of a lesser included offense is an acquittal of the greater offense even though the conviction of the lesser included offense is subsequently reversed, set aside, or vacated.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>There is a conviction if the prosecution resulted in a judgment of guilty that has not been reversed, set aside, or vacated; a verdict of guilty that has been reversed, set aside or vacated and that is capable of supporting a judgment; or a plea of guilty by the Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>There is an improper termination of prosecution if the termination takes place before the verdict, is for reasons not amounting to an acquittal, and takes place after a jury has been impaneled and sworn in, or, if the matter was to be tried without a jury, after the first witness is sworn. However, termination of prosecution is not improper if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The defendant consents to the termination; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The defendant waives his/her right to object to the termination; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The Court finds and states for the record that the termination is necessary because:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>It is physically impossible to proceed with the trial in conformity to the law; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>There is a legal defect in the proceeding which would make any judgment entered upon a verdict reversible as a matter of law; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>Prejudicial conduct, in or outside of the courtroom, makes it impossible to proceed with the trial without injustice to the defendant or to the prosecution; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(D)</num>
            <text>The jury is unable to agree on a verdict; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(E)</num>
            <text>A false statement of a juror on voir dire, when questioned during jury selection, prevents a fair trial.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>A subsequent prosecution of an offense is not barred if the former prosecution resulted in a judgment of guilt held invalid on appeal or in a subsequent proceeding on a writ of habeas corpus, coram vobis, or similar collateral attack.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>Prosecution of an offense is not barred by virtue of the fact that the defendant could be or has been charged under 18 U.S.C. §1153 (Major Crimes Act) unless such charge has, in fact, resulted in a conviction or acquittal of the defendant by a Federal Court following trial.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.01.090 was formerly codified as 4-1-9</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.01.100</num>
      <heading>Burden and Presumption of Innocence.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A defendant in a criminal proceeding is presumed to be innocent until each element of the offence against him/her is proved beyond a reasonable doubt. In the absence of such proof, the defendant shall be acquitted.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>By "element of the offense" is meant:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>The conduct, attendant circumstances or results of conduct proscribed, prohibited or forbidden in the definition of the offense; plus</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>The culpable mental state required; but</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>Jurisdiction is not an element of the offense nor is the statute of limitations or any other matter similarly unconnected with the harm or evil, incident to conduct, sought to be prevented by the offense nor is the existence   of justification or excuse as defense to the offense, and such may be established by preponderance of the evidence</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.01.100 was formerly codified as 4-1-10</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.01.110</num>
      <heading>Negative Defenses.</heading>
      <text>The prosecution need not negate any defense either in the complaint or by proof unless the defense is in issue as a result of evidence presented at trial by either side, or unless the defense is an affirmative defense and the defendant has presented evidence of such.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.01.110 was formerly codified as 4-1-11</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.01.120</num>
      <heading>Presumptions of Fact.</heading>
      <text>An evidentiary presumption established by this Code has the following consequences:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>When the evidence of facts which support the presumption exist, the issue of the existence of the presumed fact must be submitted to the jury unless the Court is satisfied that the evidence, as a whole, clearly negates the presumed fact;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>In submitting the issue of the presumed fact to the jury, the Court shall charge the jury that while the presumed fact must on all evidence be proved beyond a reasonable doubt, the law regards the facts that give rise to the presumed fact as evidence of the presumed fact.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.01.120 was formerly codified as 4-1-12</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>4.02</num>
    <heading>Principles of Criminal Responsibility</heading>
    <section>
      <num>4.02.010</num>
      <heading>Acts and Omissions to Act.</heading>
      <text>A person is not guilty of an offense unless his/her liability is based on conduct, which includes a voluntary act or the omission to perform an act of which he/she is physically capable.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The following are not voluntary acts within the meaning of <cite path="§4.02.010">this section</cite>:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>A reflex or convulsion;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>A bodily movement during unconsciousness or sleep;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Conduct during hypnosis;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>A bodily movement that otherwise is not a product of the effort or determination of the actor, either conscious or habitual.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Liability for the commission of an offense may not be based on an omission unaccompanied by action unless:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The omission is expressly made sufficient by the law defining the offense; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>A duty to perform the omitted act is otherwise imposed by law.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Possession is an act, within the meaning of <cite path="§4.02.010">this section</cite>, if the possessor knowingly procured or received the item possessed or was away of his/her control thereof for a sufficient period to have been able to terminate his/her possession.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.02.010 was formerly codified as 4-2-1</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.02.020</num>
      <heading>Culpability; General Requirements.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person is not guilty of an offense unless he/she acted purposely, knowingly, recklessly, or negligently, as the law may require, with respect to each element of the offense, or unless his/her acts constitute an offense involving strict liability.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Kinds of culpability defined are:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Purposely: a person acts purposely with respect to an element of an offense when:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>If the element involves the nature of his/her conduct or a result thereof, it is his/her conscious object to engage in conduct of that nature or to cause such a result; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>If the element involves the attendant circumstances, he/she is aware of the existence of such circumstances, or he/she believe or hopes that they exist;</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Knowingly: a person acts knowingly with respect to an element of an offense when:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>If the element involves the nature of his/her conduct or the attendant circumstances, he/she is aware that his/her conduct is of that nature or that such circumstances exist; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>If the element involves a result of his/her conduct, he/she is aware that it is practically certain that his/her conduct will cause such a result.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Recklessly: a person acts recklessly with respect to an element of an offense when he/she consciously disregards a substantial and unjustifiable risk that the element exists or will result from his/her conduct. The risk must be of such a nature and degree that, considering the nature and purpose of the person's conduct and the circumstances known to him/her, its disregard involves a gross deviation from the standard of conduct that a law-abiding person would observe in the actor's situation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Negligently: a person acts negligently with respect to an element of an offense when he/she should be aware of a substantial and unjustifiable risk that the element exists or will result from his/her conduct. The risk must be of such a nature and degree that the actor's failure to perceive it, considering the nature and purpose of their conduct and the circumstances known to them, involves a gross deviation from the standard of care that a reasonable person would observe in the actor's situation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Strict Liability: an element of an offense shall involve strict liability only when the definition of the offense or element clearly indicates a legislative purpose to impose strict liability for an element of the offense by use of the phrase "strict liability" or other terms of similar import, and when so used no proof of a culpable mental state is required to establish the commission of the element or offense.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>When the culpability sufficient to establish an element of an offense is not specifically prescribed, such element is established if a person acts purposely, knowingly, or recklessly with respect thereto.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>When the law defining an offense prescribes the kind of culpability that is sufficient for the commission of an offense, without distinguishing among the elements thereof, such provision shall apply to all the material elements of the offense, unless a contrary purpose plainly appears.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>When the law provides that negligence suffices to establish an element of an offense, such element also is established if a person acts purposely, knowingly or recklessly. When recklessness suffices to establish an element, such element is also established if a person acts purposely or knowingly. When acting knowingly suffices to establish an element, such element is also established if a person acts purposely.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>When a particular purpose is an element of an offense, the element is established although such purpose is conditional, unless the condition negates the harm or evil sought to be prevented by the offense.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>When knowledge of the existence of a particular fact is an element of an offense, such knowledge is established if a person is, or should be, aware of a high probability of its existence, unless he/she actually believes that it does not exist.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>A requirement that an offense be committed willfully is satisfied if a person acts knowingly with respect to the material elements of the offense, unless a purpose to impose further requirements appears.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text>Neither the knowledge nor recklessness nor negligence as to whether conduct constitutes an offense or as to the existence, meaning or application of the law determining the elements of an offense is an element of such offense, unless the definition of the offense so provides.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(j)</num>
        <text>When the grade or degree of an offense depends on whether the offense is committed purposely, knowingly, recklessly, or criminally negligently, its grade or degree shall be the lowest for which the determinative kind of culpability is established with respect to any material element of the offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.02.020 was formerly codified as 4-2-2</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.02.030</num>
      <heading>Causal Relationships Between Conduct and Result.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Conduct is the cause of a result when:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>It is an antecedent but for which the result in question would not have occurred; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The relationship between the conduct and result satisfies any additional causal requirements imposed by this Code or the definition of the offense.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>When a particular mental state is specified in conjunction with an element of an offense, proof of that element is not avoided because the actual result differed from that intended or that which was probable or likely under the circumstances, either in kind or degree or because a different person or property was injured or affected than that intended or than that which was probable or likely under the circumstances. Unless such differences are sufficient without consideration of the mental state involved to constitute a defense or avoidance or unless such differences are of such a magnitude that it would be unjust to find the element involved in light of such differences.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.02.030 was formerly codified as 4-2-3</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.02.040</num>
      <heading>Ignorance or Mistake.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Ignorance or mistake as to a matter of fact or law is a defense only if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The ignorance or mistake negates a specific mental state required to establish an element of the offense; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The law provided that the actual state of mind, which existed itself, constitutes a defense.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Although ignorance or mistake would otherwise afford a defense to the offense charged, the defense is not available if the defendant would be guilty of another offense if the situation had been as he/she supposed in which case the punishment available upon conviction shall not exceed that prescribed for the other offense.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>A belief that conduct does not legally constitute an offense is a defense for the prosecution of an offense based on that conduct only when:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The enactment defining the offense is not known to the person and has not been published or reasonably made available prior to the conduct alleged; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The person acted in reasonable reliance upon an official statement of law contained in a subsequent enactment or an interpretation rendered by a Judge in a written opinion. In either case the defendant shall have the burden of proving, by a preponderance of the evidence, his/her defense under <cite path="§4.02.040|(c)|(2)">Section 4.02.040(c)(2)</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.02.040 was formerly codified as 4-2-4</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.02.050</num>
      <heading>Liability for Conduct of Another.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person is guilty of an offense if it is committed by his/her own conduct or by the conduct of another person for whom he/she is legally responsible, or both.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>A person is legally responsible for the conduct of another person when:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Acting with the kind of culpability that is sufficient for the commission of the offense, he/she causes an innocent or irresponsible person to engage in such conduct; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>He/she is made responsible for the conduct of such other person by this Code or the definition of the offense; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>He/she is an accomplice of such other person in the commission of the offense.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>A person is an accomplice of another person in the commission of an offense if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>With the purpose promoting or facilitating the commission of an offense, he/she;</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Solicits such other person to commit it; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Aids, agrees or attempts to aid such person in planning or committing it; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>Having legal duty to prevent the commission of the offense, fails to make proper effort to do so; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(D)</num>
            <text>His/her conduct is expressly declared by law to establish his/her complicity.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>When causing a particular result is an element of an offense, an accomplice in the conduct causing such result, is an accomplice in the commission of that offense if he/she acts with the kind of culpability, if any, with respect to that result that is sufficient for the commission of the offense.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>A person is legally incapable of committing a particular offense him/herself may be guilty thereof if it is committed by the conduct of another person for whom he/she is legally responsible, unless such liability is inconsistent with the purpose of his/her incapacity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>Unless otherwise provided by this Code or by the law defining the offense, a person is not an accomplice in an offense committed by another person, if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>He/she is a victim of that offense; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The offense is so defined that his/her conduct is inevitably incident to its commission; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>He/she terminates his/her complicity prior to the commission of the offense and</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>wholly deprives it of effectiveness in the offense, or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>gives timely warning to law enforcement authorities or otherwise makes proper effort to prevent the commission of the offense.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>An accomplice may be convicted on proof of the commission of the offense and of his/her complicity therein, though the person claimed to have committed the offense has not been prosecuted or convicted or has been convicted of a different offense or degree of offense or has immunity from prosecution or has been acquitted.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.02.050 was formerly codified as 4-2-5</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.02.060</num>
      <heading>Corporations and Unincorporated Associations.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person is legally responsible for any conduct he/she performs or causes to be performed in the name of a corporation or unincorporated association or in its behalf to the same extent as if it were performed in his/her own name or behalf.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Whenever a duty to act is imposed by law upon a corporation or unincorporated association, any agent of the corporation or association having primary responsibility for the discharge of the duty is legally responsible for a reckless omission to perform the required act to the same extent as if the duty were imposed by law directly upon them.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>When a person is convicted of an offense by reason of his/her legal responsibility for the conduct of a corporation or an unincorporated association, he/she is subject to the sentence authorized by law when a natural person is convicted of an offense of the class involved.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.02.060 was formerly codified as 4-2-6</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.02.070</num>
      <heading>Intoxication.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in Subsection D of <cite path="§4.02.070">this section</cite>, intoxication of a person is not a defense unless it negates an element of the offense.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>When recklessness establishes an element of the offense, if a person, due to self-induced intoxication, is unaware of a risk of which he/she would have been aware had he/she been sober, such unawareness is immaterial.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Intoxication does not, in itself, constitute a mental disease as that term is used in this Code.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Intoxication which (a) is not self-induced, or (b) is the result of intoxication excessive in degree given the amount of the intoxicant, to which result the actor does not know he/she is susceptible, is an affirmative defense, if by reason of such intoxication, the person at the time of his/her conduct lacks substantial capacity either to appreciate its wrongfulness or to conform his/her conduct to the requirements of the law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>"Intoxication" means a disturbance of mental or physical capabilities and/or capacities resulting from the introduction of substances into the body. Except as otherwise provided in this Code, intoxication can be proven by its external indications and no proof of specific consumption or blood alcohol content is necessary, though such evidence is permissible to prove intoxication.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.02.070 was formerly codified as 4-2-7</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.02.080</num>
      <heading>Duress.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Except as herein otherwise provided, it is an affirmative defense that a person engaged in conduct charged to constitute an offense because he/she was coerced to do so by the use of, or threat to use, unlawful force against his/her person or the person of another, which a law abiding person of reasonable firmness in his/her situation would have been unable to resist.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The defense provided in <cite path="§4.02.080">this section</cite> is unavailable to a person who intentionally, knowingly, or recklessly places him/herself in a situation in which it is probable that he/she will be subjected to duress.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>It is not a defense that a woman acted on the command of her husband, unless she acted under such coercion as would establish a defense under Subsection A of <cite path="§4.02.080">this section</cite>. No presumption of duress arises from the mere presence of the husband at the time a woman acted.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>The defense provided in <cite path="§4.02.080">this section</cite> is unavailable in any situation where the coerced conduct threatens to cause death or serious bodily harm to some person, other than the  actor, or does in fact cause such harm.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.02.080 was formerly codified as 4-2-8</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.02.090</num>
      <heading>Consent.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The consent of the victim to conduct charged to constitute an offense or to the result thereof is a defense if such consent negates an element of the offense or precluded the infliction of the harm or evil sought to be prevented by the law defining the offense.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>When conduct is charged to constitute an offense because it threatens to cause or causes bodily harm, consent to such conduct or to the infliction of such harm is a defense only if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The bodily harm consented to or threatened by the conduct consented to is not serious; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The conduct and the harm are reasonably foreseeable hazards of joint participation in a lawful athletic contest, competitive sport or other lawful activity; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The consent establishes a justification for the conduct under this Code.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Unless otherwise provided by this Code or the law defining the offense, assent does not constitute consent if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>It is given by a person who is legally incompetent to authorize the conduct charged to constitute an offense; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>It is given by a person who by reason of youth, mental disease or defect, or intoxication is manifestly unable or known to the actor to be unable to make a reasonable judgment as to the nature or the harmfulness of the conduct charged to constitute the offense; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>It is given by a person whose improvident consent is sought to be prevented by the law defining the offense; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>It is induced by force, duress, or deception.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.02.090 was formerly codified as 4-2-9</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.02.100</num>
      <heading>Entrapment.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A public law enforcement officer or official or a person acting in cooperation with such an official perpetrates an entrapment if for the purpose of obtaining evidence of the commission of an offense, he/she induces or encourages another person to engage in conduct constituting an offense by either:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Making knowingly false representations designed to induce the belief that such conduct is not prohibited; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Employing methods of persuasion or inducement, which create a substantial risk that such an offense will be committed by persons other than those who are ready to commit it.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The defense afforded by <cite path="§4.02.100">this section</cite> shall be unavailable when causing or threatening bodily injury is an element of the offense charged and the prosecution is based on conduct causing or threatening such injury to a person other than the person perpetrating the entrapment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Except as provided in Subsection B of <cite path="§4.02.100">this section</cite>, a person prosecuted for an offense shall be acquitted if he/she proves by a preponderance of evidence that his/her conduct occurred in response to an entrapment. The issue of entrapment shall be tried to and decided by the Court and not by the jury. Evidence of past offenses shall be admissible only if the defendant takes the stand in his/her own defense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.02.100 was formerly codified as 4-2-10</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.02.110</num>
      <heading>Mental Disease or Defect</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>In any prosecution for an offense, it shall be a defense that the defendant, at the time of the conduct upon which the prosecution is based, as a result of mental disease or defect, lacked substantial capacity either to appreciate the wrongfulness of his/her conduct or to conform his/her conduct to the requirements of the law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>As used in <cite path="§4.02.110">this section</cite>, the terms "mental disease" or "defect" do not include an abnormality manifested only by repeated criminal or otherwise antisocial conduct.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The defense afforded by <cite path="§4.02.110">this section</cite> shall not be available unless notice of intent to rely on such defense is given at least two weeks before trial. By giving such notice, the defendant will be deemed to have consented to be examined for the prosecution by not more than two professional medical or other experts for the purpose of ascertaining the state of the defendant's mental health.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>No person who, as a result of mental disease or defect, lacks capacity to understand the proceedings against him/her or to assist in their own defense shall be tried, convicted, or sentenced for the commission of an offense so long as such incapacity endures.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.02.110 was formerly codified as 4-2-11</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.02.120</num>
      <heading>Justification.</heading>
      <text>Conduct, which is justified, is a defense to prosecution for any offense based on the conduct. The defense of justification may be claimed:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>When a person's conduct is in defense of persons or property or as otherwise described in the next succeeding five sections (§<cite path="§4.02.130">Section 4.02.130</cite> through §<cite path="§4.02.170">Section 4.02.170</cite>); or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>When a person's conduct is reasonable and in fulfillment of his/her duties as a Tribal or governmental officer or employee; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>When a person's conduct is reasonable discipline of minors by parents, guardians, teachers or other persons in loco parentis (in place of parent); or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>When a person's conduct is reasonable discipline of persons in custody under this Code.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.02.120 was formerly codified as 4-2-12</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.02.130</num>
      <heading>Force in Defense of Persons.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person is justified in threatening or using force against another when, and to the extent that he/she reasonably believes, that such force is necessary to defend him/herself or a third person against such other's imminent use of unlawful force; however, a person is justified in using force which is intended or likely to cause death or serious bodily injury only if he/she reasonably believes that such force is necessary to prevent death or serious bodily injury to him/herself or a third person.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>A person is not justified in using force under the circumstances specified in Subsection A of <cite path="§4.02.130">this section</cite> if he/she:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Initially provokes the use of force against him/herself with the intent to use force against as an excuse to inflict bodily harm upon the assailant; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Is, attempting to commit, committing, or fleeing after the commission of an offense; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Was the aggressor or was engaged in a combat by agreement, unless he/she withdraws from the encounter and effectively communicates to such other person his/her intent to do so and the other, notwithstanding, continues or threatens to continue the use of unlawful force,</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.02.130 was formerly codified as 4-2-13</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.02.140</num>
      <heading>Force in Arrest.</heading>
      <text>Any person is justified in using any force, except deadly force, which he/she reasonably believes to be necessary to affect an arrest or to defend him/herself or another from bodily harm while making an arrest.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.02.140 was formerly codified as 4-2-14</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.02.150</num>
      <heading>Deadly Force by Law Enforcement Officer.</heading>
      <text>A law enforcement officer or any person acting by his/her command in his/her aid and assistance is justified in using deadly force when:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>In effecting the arrest or preventing an escape from custody following an arrest and the officer reasonably believes that both:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Such force is necessary to prevent the arrest from being defeated by resistance or escape; and;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The person to be arrested is attempting to escape by use of a deadly weapon.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The officer is in the performance of his/her legal duty or the execution of legal process and reasonably believes the use of force is necessary to protect themselves or others from imminent danger to life.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.02.150 was formerly codified as 4-2-15</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.02.160</num>
      <heading>Force in Defense of Habitation.</heading>
      <text>A person is justified in using force against another when, and to the extent, that he/she reasonably believes that the force is necessary to prevent or terminate the other's unlawful entry into or attack upon their place of habitation; however, he/she is justified in the use of force which is intended or likely to cause death or serious bodily injury only if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The entry is made or attempted in a violent and tumultuous manner and he/she reasonably believes that the entry is attempted or made for the purpose of assaulting or offering personal violence to any dwelling or person therein, and that the force is necessary to prevent the assault or offering of personal violence; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>He/she reasonably believes that the entry is made or attempted for the purpose of committing a Class A offense or other offense involving threat of bodily injury therein, and that such force is necessary to prevent the commission of such offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.02.160 was formerly codified as 4-2-16</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.02.170</num>
      <heading>Force in Defense of Property.</heading>
      <text>A person is justified in using or threatening to use force, other than deadly force, against another when and to the extent that he/she reasonably believes that force is necessary to prevent or terminate criminal interference with real or personal property, when that property is:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Lawfully in his/her possession; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Lawfully in the possession of his/her immediate family; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Belonging to a person whose property he/she has a legal duty to protect.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.02.170 was formerly codified as 4-2-17</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.02.180</num>
      <heading>Justification of a Defense; Civil Remedies.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>In any prosecution based on conduct, which is justified as specified in this Code, such justification is an affirmative defense.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The fact that conduct is justifiable as specified in this Code does not abolish or impair any civil right or remedy, which might arise from such conduct.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.02.180 was formerly codified as 4-2-18</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>4.03</num>
    <heading>Sentences and Punishment</heading>
    <section>
      <num>4.03.010</num>
      <heading>Sentencing in General.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person adjudged guilty of an offense under this Code shall be sentenced in accordance in accordance with <cite path="4|4.03">this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Penal laws enacted or adopted after the effective date of this Code shall be classified for sentencing purposes in accordance with the provisions of <cite path="4|4.03">this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.03.010 was formerly codified as 4-3-1</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.03.020</num>
      <heading>Designation of Offenses.</heading>
      <text>Offenses are designated as Class A offenses, Class B offenses, and Class C offenses.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.03.020 was formerly codified as 4-3-2</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.03.030</num>
      <heading>Class of Offense Not Specified.</heading>
      <text>Any offense for which no penalty or sentence is specified, or which is not specifically designated as a certain class of offense, shall be treated for purposes of sentencing and punishment as a Class C offense.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.03.030 was formerly codified as 4-3-3</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.03.040</num>
      <heading>General Principles.</heading>
      <text>The sentence imposed in each case should call for the minimum amount of custody or confinement, which is consistent with the protection of the public, the severity of the offense, and the rehabilitative needs of the defendant.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.03.040 was formerly codified as 4-3-4</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.03.050</num>
      <heading>Sentences and Combinations of Sentences; Civil, Penalties.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A Court may, as provided in <cite path="4|4.03">this chapter</cite>, sentence a person adjudged guilty of an offense to any one of the following sentences or a combination of such sentences:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>To pay a fine; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Removal from and/or disqualification of public or private office, but only if such is specifically provided for as a punishment for conviction of a specific offense; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Probation and/or suspension of sentence on such terms and conditions as the Court may direct; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Imprisonment or confinement, either full or part time.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>A Court shall also have the authority to order a person found guilty of an offense to pay any or all of the following amounts or to do the following acts:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Pay court costs not to exceed fifty dollars ($50.00); or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Pay any civil penalty provided by law; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Pay money damages, surrender property, or perform any other act for the benefit of any person or party injured personally, or in his/her property, by the person found guilty, provided such injuries are fairly attributable to the act or failure to act constituting the offense for which guilty was adjudged.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>This part shall not deprive a Court of authority to cite for contempt, cancel or suspend a license, forfeit property, or do any other act or make any other order authorized by law.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.03.050 was formerly codified as 4-3-5</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.03.060</num>
      <heading>Maximum Fines and Sentences of Imprisonment.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person convicted of an offense may be sentences as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Class A offense – to a term of imprisonment not to exceed twelve (12) months and to a fine not to exceed five-thousand dollars ($5,000.00);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Class B offense – to a term of imprisonment not to exceed six (6) months and to a fine not to exceed one-thousand dollars ($1,000.00);</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Class C offense – to a term of imprisonment not to exceed forty-five (45) days and to a fine not to exceed five-hundred dollars ($500.00).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The terms of imprisonment listed above apply only to full-time incarceration in a BIA contracted or managed facility and do not apply to full-time or part-time residence or confinement in a medical or rehabilitative facility as a condition of probation or parole or as otherwise ordered by the Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The fines listed above may be imposed in addition to any assessment of costs or other civil penalties and in addition to any amounts ordered by the Court to be paid as restitution.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.03.060 was formerly codified as 4-3-6</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.03.070</num>
      <heading>Payment of Fines and Other Monies.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Fines shall be paid by money order or certified check only, or with the consent of the Court, may be worked off by performing approved labor for the Pueblo of Picuris, at a rate of ten dollars ($10.00) per hour, or as otherwise established by the Tribal Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Court may, upon request of a defendant or upon its own motion, allow that any fine or other required payments be paid in installments and on conditions tailored to the means of the defendant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The imposition of incarceration should not be imposed as an automatic alternative to payment of a fine or other money, but rather the Court should, upon default to pay a fine or other money as required, examine the reason for the default and may, if justice requires, impose an additional sentence of incarceration of no more than one day of incarceration for each one- hundred dollars ($100.00) of the required money left unpaid.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>The methods available for collecting a civil judgment shall be available to collect any unpaid money upon order of the Court following a failure to make any required payment and ascertainment of a reason thereof.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>When justice requires, the Court may revoke or remit a fine or any unpaid portion thereof or any other monies required to be paid, or may modify the terms and conditions of payment.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.03.070 was formerly codified as 4-3-7</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.03.080</num>
      <heading>Decision to Impose a Fine.</heading>
      <text>In determining whether to impose a fine and its amount, the Court should consider:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The financial resources of the defendant and the burden that payment of a fine will impose with due regard to his/her other obligations;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The ability of the defendant to pay a fine on an installment basis or on other conditions to be fixed by the Court;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The extent to which payment of a fine will interfere with the ability of the defendant to make any ordered restitution or reparation to the victim of the crime; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Whether there are particular reasons which make a fine appropriate as a deterrent to the offense involved or appropriate as a corrective measure for the defendant.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.03.080 was formerly codified as 4-3-8</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.03.090</num>
      <heading>Concurrent and Consecutive Sentences.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Unless the Court shall direct otherwise in its pronouncement of sentence, all sentences shall run concurrently and not consecutively.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Court shall consider the gravity and circumstances of the offenses and the history, character, and rehabilitative needs of the defendant as well the need to protect the public in determining whether to impose consecutive sentences.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The Court shall not impose consecutive sentences for offenses arising out of a single course of criminal conduct, including solicitation and criminal conspiracy, unless the criminal conduct involved the death or serious bodily injury of any victim of the crime or a serious threat of such, unless the offense was committed in a willful, malicious or aggravated manner and involved an offense against the person of the victim or victims.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>In no event shall the maximum term of imprisonment imposed exceed three (3) years from the date of sentencing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Whenever a sentence is imposed or sentences are imposed to run concurrently with the other or with sentences presently being served, the greater sentence shall be the term to be served with all lesser sentences merging therein, or, if equal sentences are imposed, they shall merge into one sentence, but in no event shall the imposition of one sentence cut short the time to be served on another sentence unless the Court specifically directs that such be the result.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.03.090 was formerly codified as 4-3-9</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.03.100</num>
      <heading>Credit.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Credit against a term of imprisonment imposed following an adjudication of guilty shall be given to a defendant for all time spent in custody as a result of the criminal charge for which the sentence is imposed or as a result of the conduct on which such charge is based. Such credit shall apply to time spent in custody prior to trial, during trial, pending sentencing, and pending resolution of an appeal.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>In case of re-prosecution for any reason of the same offense or an offense based on the same conduct for which a defendant has been imprisoned, credit shall be given for all time spent in custody under the prior prosecution as provided in Subsection A. above.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Credit as provided in <cite path="§4.03.100">this section</cite> should be considered and computed by the Court at the time of sentencing.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.03.100 was formerly codified as 4-3-10</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.03.110</num>
      <heading>Reduction of Sentences.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The Court may, upon motion of any party or on its own motion, reduce or modify a sentence within a reasonable time after its imposition as provided on the Rules of Criminal Procedure if new factors bearing on the sentence become known. Such reduction or modification shall be done in open Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>In the event that commitment to a special type of facility, other than a detention facility, is imposed or accepted as a condition of probation or parole, the Court may for good cause shown, terminate or reduce such commitment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The Court shall have authority to terminate, at any time, continued supervision or the power to revoke either a sentence not involving confinement or a sentence involving less than total confinement in a detention facility. The Court shall also have the power to lessen the conditions on which such sentences were imposed or lessen the time in which the power to revoke will exist.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Except as otherwise specifically provided in <cite path="4|4.03">this chapter</cite>, the Court shall not increase a term of imprisonment once it has been imposed.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.03.110 was formerly codified as 4-3-11</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.03.120</num>
      <heading>Sentencing Proceeding.</heading>
      <text>As soon as practicable after the determination of guilt and the examination of any presentence reports or recommendations, a proceeding should be held at which the Court shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Hear submission by the parties on the facts relevant to the sentence;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Hear argument by the defendant or his/her counsel on the applicability of various sentencing alternatives to the facts of the case;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Afford the defendant the opportunity to make a statement to the Court;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>In cases where guilt was determined by plea, be informed of the existence of plea discussions or agreements and the extent to which they involve recommendations as to the appropriate sentence;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Make specific findings on all refuted issues of fact which are deemed relevant to the sentencing decision;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>Ascertain and consider all credits due the defendant as a result of prior periods of incarceration;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>Carefully state and assure that a record is made of the precise terms of the sentence imposed and assure that those responsible for the executing the sentence be informed of such terms;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>State for the record the reasons for selecting the particular sentence imposed, unless the Court deems it to be in the best interests of the defendant not to do so.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.03.120 was formerly codified as 4-3-12</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.03.130</num>
      <heading>Suspension of Sentence and Probation.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Except as otherwise provided in this Code, the Court shall have the authority to suspend the imposition of sentence on a person who has been convicted of an offense and place him/her on probation as provided herein.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>When the Court suspends the imposition of sentence on a person who has been convicted of a crime or sentences him/her to be placed on probation, it shall attach such reasonable conditions as authorized herein, as it deems necessary to insure that he/she will lead a law abiding life or likely to assist him/her to do so.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The Court, as a condition of its order of probation, may require the defendant to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Meet his/her family responsibilities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Devote him/herself to a specific employment or occupation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Undergo available medical, psychiatric or other rehabilitative treatment and to enter and remain in a specified institution and/or center, when required for that purpose;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Pursue a prescribed secular course of study or vocational training;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Attend or reside in a facility established for the instruction, recreation or residence of persons on probation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Refrain from frequenting unlawful or disreputable places, or consorting with disreputable persons;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>Refrain from all use of intoxicants, narcotics or drugs, unless taken or used under a doctor's orders and obtained by a doctor's prescription;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(8)</num>
          <text>Have in his/her possession no firearms or other dangerous weapons unless written permission is granted by the Court;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(9)</num>
          <text>Make restitution for the fruits of his/her crime or to make reparation, in an amount he/she can afford to pay, for the loss of damage caused thereby;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(10)</num>
          <text>Remain within the jurisdiction of the Court and to notify the Court or the probation officer of any change of address or employment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(11)</num>
          <text>Report as directed to the Court or the probation officer and to permit the officer to visit his/her home;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(12)</num>
          <text>Satisfy any other conditions reasonably related to the rehabilitation of the defendant and not incompatible with his/her freedom of conscience or unduly restrictive of his/her liberty given his/her status as a probationer.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>When the Court sentences a person who has been convicted of a Class A offense or a Class B offense to be placed on probation, it may require him/her to serve a term of imprisonment not to exceed thirty (30) days in the case of a Class A offense and fifteen (15) days in the case of a Class B offense, as an additional condition of its order. Such term of imprisonment shall be counted as part of the period of the probation, but shall not count as part of any sentenced pronounced as a result of a revocation of probation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>The defendant shall be given a copy of the requirements of his/her probation stated with sufficient specificity to enable him/her to guide him/herself accordingly.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.03.130 was formerly codified as 4-3-13</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.03.140</num>
      <heading>Period of Suspension or Probation; Modification.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>When the Court has suspended a sentence and/or has sentenced a defendant to be placed on probation, the maximum period of the suspension or probation shall be two (2) years, provided, however, that the maximum period will be imposed for Class B and Class C offenses only when such appears to be consistent with the rehabilitative needs of the defendant. Shorter periods may be imposed at the Court's discretion.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>During the period of suspension or probation, the Court, on application of the probation officer or of the defendant, or on its own motion, may modify the requirements imposed on the defendant or add further requirements consistent with the rehabilitative needs of the defendant or may discharge the defendant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Upon termination of the period of suspension or probation, or other earlier discharge of the defendant, the defendant shall be relieved of any obligations imposed by Order of the Court and shall have satisfied his/her sentence for the offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.03.140 was formerly codified as 4-3-14</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.03.150</num>
      <heading>Violation of Terms of Suspension or Probation.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>At any time before the discharge of the defendant or the termination of the period of suspension or probation:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The Court may summon the defendant to appear before it or it may issue a warrant for his/her arrest;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>A probation or law enforcement officer, having probable cause to believe the defendant has failed to comply with a requirement imposed as a condition of the probation order or that he/she has committed another crime may arrest him/her without a warrant;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The Court, if there is probable cause to believe the defendant has committed another crime or if he/she has been held to answer therefore, may commit him/her without bail, pending a determination of the charge by the Court;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>The Court, if satisfied that the defendant has inexcusably failed to comply with a substantial requirement imposed as a condition of the probation order, or if he/she has been convicted of another crime, may revoke the suspension or probation and sentence or resentence the defendant as provided in this Code.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>When the Court revokes a suspension or probation, it may impose on the defendant any sentence that might have been imposed originally for the crime for which he/she was convicted, except that the defendant shall not be sentenced to imprisonment unless:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>He/she was convicted of another crime; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>His/her conduct indicates that his/her continued liberty involves undue risk that he/she will commit another crime; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Such disposition is essential to vindicate the authority of the Court.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The Court shall not revoke suspension or probation or increase the requirements imposed thereby except after a hearing upon written notice to the defendant on the grounds at which such action is proposed. The defendant shall have the right to hear and controvert the evidence against him/her, to offer evidence in his/her defense and to be represented by counsel of his/her choice at his/her own expense.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Whenever a defendant is taken into and held in custody as provided in <cite path="§4.03.150">this section</cite> for violation of probation conditions other than the alleged commission of an offense, he/she shall be entitled to have his/her sentence considered by the Court within 48 hours of his/her confinement, unless he/she requests further time to prepare his/her defense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.03.150 was formerly codified as 4-3-15</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.03.160</num>
      <heading>Order Removing Disqualification or Disability Based on Conviction.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>When the Court has suspended a sentence or has sentenced the defendant to be placed on probation and the defendant has fully complied with the requirements imposed as a condition of such order and has satisfied the sentence, the Court may order that so long as the defendant is not convicted on another offense, the judgment shall not constitute a conviction for the purpose of any disqualification or disability imposed by law upon conviction of a crime or offense.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Proof of a conviction as relevant evidence upon the trial or determination of any issue or for the purpose of impeaching the defendant as a witness is not a disqualification or disability within the meaning of <cite path="§4.03.160">this section</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.03.160 was formerly codified as 4-3-16</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.03.170</num>
      <heading>Final Judgment.</heading>
      <text>A judgment suspending sentence or sentencing a defendant to be placed on probation shall be deemed tentative to the extent such is modifiable as provided herein, but for all other purposes shall constitute a final judgment.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.03.170 was formerly codified as 4-3-17</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.03.180</num>
      <heading>Eligibility for Parole.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Except as otherwise provided herein, a defendant sentenced to and serving a term of imprisonment for more than sixty (60) days shall be eligible to petition the Court for a grant of release on parole.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Parole may be granted as provided herein to a defendant who has demonstrated good behavior and faithful performance of duties while incarcerated.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Parole shall not be considered or granted to a defendant who has been convicted of an offense involving the death or serious bodily injury of a victim of the offense unless the defendant has been sentenced to consecutive sentences totaling in excess of one (1) year and such consideration may be given only after the defendant has served one (1) year under such sentences.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>The provisions on parole contained herein shall apply only to confinement in a jail or penitentiary and shall not apply to confinement ordered in a medical or rehabilitative facility.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.03.180 was formerly codified as 4-3-18</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.03.190</num>
      <heading>Petition for Parole.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Parole may be granted by the Court on its own motion or on the petition of an incarcerated defendant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Any defendant eligible for parole as set forth above may petition the Court for consideration of parole. Such petition may be made on a form to be provided for such purposes by the Court, at a time no earlier than the expiration of half the period of imprisonment ordered by the Court. If a defendant desires, he/she will be allowed opportunity to contact and meet with counsel on the detention facility premises to aid him/her in the preparation of his/her petition for parole. The completed petition shall be forwarded without unnecessary delay to the Court by the defendant's counsel or by the detention facility.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.03.190 was formerly codified as 4-3-19</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.03.200</num>
      <heading>Consideration for Parole.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The Court, upon receipt of a petition for parole, shall cause the Clerk of the Court to prepare a report stating the term for which the defendant was sentenced, the offense(s) charged, the time served and may include a sworn statement from a detention facility caseworker regarding the conduct of the defendant while incarcerated and any other information deemed relevant by the Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Unless it appears that the defendant is not eligible for parole as a result of some reason other than his/her behavior while incarcerated, the Judge shall schedule a parole hearing within fourteen (14) days and may request a report from a probation officer on the background and rehabilitative needs of the defendant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>A hearing shall be held at which time the defendant shall have the right to be represented by counsel, at their own expense, and present evidence. The Court may, upon consideration of all relevant factors, grant parole to a defendant upon any or all of the conditions set forth in this Code for granting of probation and for like periods as if probation were then imposed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>The Court's decision to grant or refuse parole shall be reviewable only for abuse of discretion.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.03.200 was formerly codified as 4-3-20</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.03.210</num>
      <heading>Powers over Parolee.</heading>
      <text>Once parole is granted, the defendant shall be subject to the same procedures and conditions as if he/she were originally placed on probation and the Court shall have the power to modify or revoke the probation under like rules and circumstances as provided in this Code for defendants on probation.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.03.210 was formerly codified as 4-3-21</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>4.04</num>
    <heading>Offenses and Penalties.</heading>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.010</num>
      <heading>Abandonment of a Dependent.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of abandonment of a dependent if that person, having the ability and means to provide for his/her spouse and minor child's support, and abandoning or failing to provide for the support of such dependent and thereby leaving such spouse or minor child dependent upon public support.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Abandonment of a Dependent is a Class B offense. The parents/guardians may also be ordered to pay child support and/or reimburse the costs related to transport, shelter care, and out of home placement.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.010 was formerly codified as 4-4-101</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.020</num>
      <heading>Abandonment or Abuse of a Child.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of abandonment or abuse of a child who has not reached eighteen (18) years of age, if that person as a parent, guardian, or custodian of that child:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Willfully leaves or abandons the child under circumstances whereby the child may or does suffer neglect. For purposes of <cite path="§4.04.020">this section</cite>, "neglect" means that a child is without proper parental care and control of subsistence, education, medical or other care or control necessary for his/her well-being because of the faults or habits of his/her parents, guardian or custodian or their neglect or refusal, when able to do so, to provide for them;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Knowingly or negligently and without justifiable cause, permits or places a child in a situation that may endanger the child's life or health;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Torture, cruelly confine or cruelly punish a child; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Expose the child to the elements of severe weather.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Abandonment or abuse of a child is a Class B offense. The parents/guardians may also be ordered to pay child support and/or reimburse the costs related to transport, shelter care and out of home placement.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.020 was formerly codified as 4-4-100</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.030</num>
      <heading>Abduction.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of abduction if that person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Takes, detains, or entices a child under eighteen (18) years of age, away from the custody of his/her parents or other lawful custodian;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Takes away or detains another person against his/her will.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Abduction is a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.030 was formerly codified as 4-4-20</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.040</num>
      <heading>Aggravated Assault.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of aggravated assault if that person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Unlawfully assaults or strikes at another person with a deadly weapon;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Commits assault by threatening or menacing another person while wearing a mask, hood, robe, or other covering upon the face, head, or body, or while disguised in any manner, so as to conceal identity; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Willfully and intentionally assault another with the intent to commit another crime.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Aggravated Assault is a Class A offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.040 was formerly codified as 4-4-8</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.043</num>
      <heading>Aggravated Assault Against a Household Member.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Aggravated assault against a household member consists of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Unlawfully assaulting or striking a household member with a deadly weapon; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Willfully and intentionally assaulting a household member with intent to commit any Class A offense.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Aggravated assault against a household member is a Class A offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.043 was formerly codified as 4-4-10</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.047</num>
      <heading>Aggravated Assault on a Law Enforcement Officer.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of aggravated assault upon a law enforcement officer if that person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Unlawfully assaults or strikes at a law enforcement officer with a deadly weapon while that officer is in the lawful discharge of his/her duties; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Commits assault by threatening or menacing a law enforcement officer who is engaged in the lawful discharge of his/her duties by a person wearing a mask, hood, robe, or other covering upon the face, head, or body, or while disguised in an manner, so as to conceal identity; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Willfully and intentionally assaults a law enforcement officer while that officer is in the lawful discharge of his/her duties with the intent to commit a crime.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Aggravated assault upon a law enforcement officer is a Class A offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.047 was formerly codified as 4-4-12</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.050</num>
      <heading>Aggravated Battery.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of aggravated battery if that person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Unlawfully touches or applies force to the person of another with the intent to injure that person causing painful temporary disfigurement or temporary loss or impairment of the functions of any member or organ of the body;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Inflicts great bodily harm on another and does so with a deadly weapon or does so in any manner whereby great bodily harm or death can be inflicted.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Aggravated battery is a Class A offense. Upon conviction hereof, at the discretion of the Court, such offender may be required to pay any hospital and/or doctor bills for treatment of injuries; and/or to pay restitution to the victim.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.050 was formerly codified as 4-4-16</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.053</num>
      <heading>Aggravated Battery Against a Household Member.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Aggravated battery against a household member consists of the unlawful touching or application of force to the person of a household member with the intent to injure that person or another.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Whoever commits aggravated battery against a household member by inflicting an injury to that person that is not likely to cause death or great bodily harm, but causes painful temporary disfigurement or temporary loss or impairment of the functions of any member or organ of the body, is guilty of a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Whoever commits aggravated battery against a household member by inflicting great bodily harm or doing so with a deadly weapon or doing so in any manner whereby great bodily harm or death can be inflicted is guilty of a Class A offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.053 was formerly codified as 4-4-17</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.057</num>
      <heading>Aggravated Battery on a Law Enforcement Officer.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of aggravated battery upon a law enforcement officer if that person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Unlawfully touches or applies force to the person of a law enforcement officer while that officer is in the lawful discharge of his/her duties, with the intent to injure that officer causing painful temporary disfigurement or temporary loss or impairment of the functions of any member or organ of the body;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Inflicts great bodily harm upon a law enforcement officer while that officer is in the lawful discharge of his/her duties and does so with a deadly weapon or does so in any many whereby great bodily harm or death can be inflicted.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Aggravated battery upon a law enforcement officer is a Class A offense. Upon conviction thereof, at the discretion of the Court, such offender may be required to pay any hospital and/or doctor bills for treatment of injuries; and/or to pay restitution to the victim.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.057 was formerly codified as 4-4-18</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.060</num>
      <heading>Aggravated Criminal Sexual Contact.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of aggravated criminal sexual contact if that person unlawfully and intentionally touches or applies force, without consent to the unclothed intimate parts of another who is at least eighteen (18) years of age, and is not a spouse to that person; or causes another person other than that person's spouse, who is at least eighteen (18) years of age to touch his/her intimate parts by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Using force or coercion resulting in personal injury to the victim; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Armed with a deadly weapon.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Aggravated criminal sexual contact is a Class A offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.060 was formerly codified as 4-4-94</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.065</num>
      <heading>Aggravated Criminal Sexual Contact of a Minor.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of aggravated criminal sexual contact of a minor if that person unlawfully and intentionally touches or applies force without consent to the intimate parts of a minor who is under eighteen (18) years of age; or causes that minor to touch his/her intimate parts, when:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>That person is in a position of authority over the minor and uses that authority to coerce the minor to submit;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>That person uses force or coercion resulting in personal injury; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>That person is armed with a deadly weapon.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Aggravated criminal sexual contact of a minor is a Class A offense. The Court may order such offenders to be mentally evaluated. Upon conviction, the defendant will be required to register as a convicted sex offender with the State of New Mexico and may be subject to exclusion from the Pueblo of Picuris. The Court may order such offender to pay restitution to the victim for all unreimbursed expense relating to medical and psychological treatment without limitations to time. Those expenses covered by insurance may also be ordered under restitution.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.065 was formerly codified as 4-4-96</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.070</num>
      <heading>Aggravated Stalking.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Aggravated stalking consists of stalking perpetrated by a person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Who knowingly violates a permanent or temporary order of protection issued by a Court, except that mutual violations of such orders may constitute a defense to a charge of aggravated stalking;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>In violation of a Court Order setting conditions of release on bond;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>When the person is in possession of a deadly weapon; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>When the victim is less than sixteen (16) years of age.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Aggravated stalking is a Class A offense. In addition to any punishment provided pursuant to the provisions of <cite path="§4.04.070">this section</cite>, the Court shall order a person convicted of aggravated stalking to participate in and complete a program of professional counseling at his/her own expense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.070 was formerly codified as 4-4-26</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.080</num>
      <heading>Aggravated Weapons Offense.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person is guilty of aggravated weapons offense if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>He/she carries a dangerous weapon concealed on his/her person; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>He/she threatens to use or exhibits a dangerous weapon in a dangerous and threatening manner, or uses a dangerous weapon in a fight or quarrel; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>He/she possesses a shotgun or rifle having a barrel(s) of less than sixteen (16) inches in length or an altered or modified shotgun or rifle less than twenty-six (26) inches overall length.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Aggravated weapons offense is a Class A offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.080 was formerly codified as 4-4-67</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.090</num>
      <heading>Aiding or Soliciting a Suicide.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person is guilty of aiding or soliciting a suicide if he/she purposely aids or solicits another to commit suicide.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Aiding or soliciting a suicide is a Class A offense, if the defendant's conduct has actually caused or contributed substantially to a suicide or an attempted suicide; otherwise it is a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.090 was formerly codified as 4-4-6</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.100</num>
      <heading>Arson.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of arson if that person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Maliciously or willfully starts a fire or causes an explosion with the purpose of destroying or damaging any building, occupied structure, bridge, utility line, fence, sign, or other property of another with the purpose of destroying or damaging such property; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Maliciously or willfully starts a fire or causes an explosion with the purpose of destroying or damaging his/her own property or the property of another, to collect insurance for such loss.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Arson is a Class B offense. The Court may order such offender to pay restitution for damages.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.100 was formerly codified as 4-4-87</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.110</num>
      <heading>Assault.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of assault if that person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Attempts to commit a battery upon the person of another;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Acts unlawfully in a threatening or menacing manner which causes another person to reasonably believe that he/she is in danger of receiving an immediate battery; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Uses insulting language toward another person attacking his/her honor or reputation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Assault is a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.110 was formerly codified as 4-4-7</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.113</num>
      <heading>Assault Against a Household Member.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Assault against a household member consists of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>An attempt to commit a battery against a household member; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Any unlawful act, threat, or menacing conduct that causes a household member to reasonably believe that they are in danger of receiving an immediate battery.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Assault against a household member is a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.113 was formerly codified as 4-4-9</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.117</num>
      <heading>Assault upon a Law Enforcement Officer.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of assault upon a law enforcement officer if that person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Attempts to commit upon the person of a law enforcement officer while that officer is in the lawful discharge of his/her duties; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Acts unlawfully in a threatening or menacing manner which causes a law enforcement officer while that officer is in the lawful discharge of his/her duties to reasonably believe that he/she is in danger of receiving an immediate battery.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Assault upon a law enforcement officer is a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.117 was formerly codified as 4-4-11</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.120</num>
      <heading>Battery.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of battery if that person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Willfully strikes another person or otherwise intentionally inflicts bodily injury on another; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Who shall cause another person to harm themself.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Battery is a Class B offense. Upon conviction, at the discretion of the Court, such offender may be required to pay any hospital and/or doctor bills for treatment of injuries; and/or to pay restitution to the victim.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.120 was formerly codified as 4-4-13</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.123</num>
      <heading>Battery Against a Household Member.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Battery against a household member consists of the unlawful, intentional touching or application of force to the person of a household member, when done in a rude, insolent, or angry manner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Battery against a household member is a Class B offense. Upon conviction, pursuant to <cite path="§4.04.123">this section</cite>, an offender shall be required to participate in and complete a domestic violence offender treatment program.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.123 was formerly codified as 4-4-14</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.127</num>
      <heading>Battery on a Law Enforcement Officer.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of battery upon a law enforcement officer if that person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Willfully strikes the person of a law enforcement officer or otherwise intentionally inflict bodily injury on a law enforcement officer while that officer is in the lawful discharge of his/her duties.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Battery upon a law enforcement officer is a Class B offense. Upon conviction thereof, at the discretion of the Court, such offender may be required to pay any hospital and/or doctor bills for treatment of injuries; and/or to pay restitution to the victim.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.127 was formerly codified as 4-4-15</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.130</num>
      <heading>Breaking and Entering.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of breaking and entering if that person breaks into any vehicle, dwelling, or other structure by breaking or dismantling any device used to secure such property and enters such property without the permission of the owner, for the purpose to commit a crime.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Breaking and entering is a Class A offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.130 was formerly codified as 4-4-58</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.140</num>
      <heading>Bribery.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of bribery if that person gives or offers to give, directly or indirectly, anything of value to any tribal officer with the intent to induce or influence the tribal officer to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Give or render any official opinion, judgment, or decree;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Be more favorable to one party than to the other in any cause, action, suit, election, appointment, matter or thing pending or to be brought before such person.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Procure him/her to vote or withhold his/her vote on any question, matter or proceeding which is then or may thereafter be pending, and which may, by law, come or be brought before him/her in his/her public capacity;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Execute any of the powers vested in him/her;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Perform any public duty otherwise than as required by law, or to delay in or omit to perform any public duty required of him/her by law.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Bribery is a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.140 was formerly codified as 4-4-84</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.145</num>
      <heading>Bribery of or Tampering with a Witness.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of bribery or tampering with a witness if that person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Gives or offers to give anything of value to any witness, or to any person likely to become a witness in any judicial, administrative, legislative, or other official cause or proceeding pending or about to be brought before, to testify falsely or to abstain from testifying to any fact in any cause or proceeding; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Intimidates or threatens any witness, or person likely to become a witness in any judicial, administrative, legislative, or other official cause or proceeding pending or about to be brought, for the purpose of preventing such individual from testifying to any fact, to abstain from testifying, or to testify falsely.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Bribery or tampering with a witness is a Class A offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.145 was formerly codified as 4-4-86</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.150</num>
      <heading>Bringing Contraband into a Place of Confinement.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of bringing contraband into a place of confinement, if that person, by carrying or transporting any contraband into the premises; or deposits any contraband onto the grounds of a place of confinement. Contraband shall be considered as:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Any deadly weapon, including ammunition, explosive devices and explosive materials; this does not include a weapon carried by a law enforcement officer in the lawful discharge of their duties;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Any alcoholic beverage;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Any controlled substance, as defined in the Controlled Substances Act.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Bringing contraband into a place of confinement is a Class A offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.150 was formerly codified as 4-4-79</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.160</num>
      <heading>Burglary.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of burglary if that person, without authorization, enters any vehicle, dwelling, or other structure with the intent to commit a crime or theft therein.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Burglary is a Class A offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.160 was formerly codified as 4-4-57</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.170</num>
      <heading>Causing a Suicide.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person is guilty of causing a suicide if he/she purposely causes a suicide by force, duress, or deception.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Causing a suicide is a Class A offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.170 was formerly codified as 4-4-5</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.180</num>
      <heading>Concealing Identity.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of concealing identity if that person conceals his/her true name or identity, or disguises him/herself with the intent to obstruct the due execution of the law or with the intent to intimidate, hinder or interrupt any law enforcement officer or any other person in the legal performance of their duties.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Concealing identity is a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.180 was formerly codified as 4-4-75</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.190</num>
      <heading>Contributing to the Delinquency of a Minor.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of contributing to the delinquency of a minor if that person commits any act or omits the performance of any duty, which act or omission causes or tends to cause or encourage the delinquency of any minor who is under eighteen (18) years of age, including, but not limited to, offering such underage minor alcoholic beverages.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Contributing to the delinquency of a minor is a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.190 was formerly codified as 4-4-102</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.200</num>
      <heading>Criminal Homicide.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person is guilty of criminal homicide if he/she purposely, knowingly, recklessly or negligently causes the death of another human being.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Criminal homicide is a Class A offense, and if the offense is found to have been committed purposely or knowingly, no suspension of sentence, probation or parole shall be granted, and the maximum fine and incarceration shall be imposed.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.200 was formerly codified as 4-4-3</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.210</num>
      <heading>Criminal Sexual Contact.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of criminal sexual contact if that person unlawfully and intentionally touches or applies force, without consent to the unclothed intimate parts of another who is at least eighteen (18) years of age and is not a spouse to that person; or causes another person other than that person's spouse, who is at least eighteen (18) years of age to touch his/her intimate parts. For the purpose of <cite path="§4.04.210">this section</cite>, "intimate parts" means the primary genital area, groin, buttocks, anus or breast.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Criminal sexual contact is a Class A offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.210 was formerly codified as 4-4-93</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.215</num>
      <heading>Criminal Sexual Contact of a Minor.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of criminal sexual contact of a minor if that person unlawfully and intentionally touches or applies force without consent to the intimate parts of a minor who is under eighteen (18) years of age; or causes that minor to touch his/her intimate parts.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Criminal sexual contact of a minor is a Class A offense. The Court may order such offenders to be mentally evaluated. Upon conviction, the defendant will be required to register as a convicted sex offender with the State of New Mexico, and may be subject to exclusion from the Pueblo of Picuris. The Court may order such offender to pay restitution to the victim for all unreimbursed expense relating to medical and psychological treatment without limitations to time. Those expenses covered by insurance may also be ordered under restitution.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.215 was formerly codified as 4-4-95</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.220</num>
      <heading>Criminal Sexual Penetration.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of criminal sexual penetration if that person unlawfully and intentionally causes another person to engage in sexual intercourse, cunnilingus, fellatio or anal intercourse or the causing of penetration, to any extent and with any object, of the genital or anal openings of another, whether or not there is any emission by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The use of force or coercion that results in personal injury to the victim;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The use of force or coercion when the perpetrator is aided or abetted by one or more persons;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>In the commission of any other crime; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>When the perpetrator is armed with a deadly weapon.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Criminal sexual penetration is a Class A offense. The Court may order such offenders to be mentally evaluated. Upon conviction, the defendant will be required to register as a convicted sex offender with the State of New Mexico and may be subject to exclusion from the Pueblo of Picuris. The Court may order such offender to pay restitution to the victim for all unreimbursed expense relating to medical and psychological treatment without limitations to time. Those expenses covered by insurance may also be ordered under restitution.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.220 was formerly codified as 4-4-97</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.225</num>
      <heading>Criminal Sexual Penetration of a Minor</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of criminal sexual penetration of a minor if that person unlawfully and intentionally causes a minor who is under eighteen (18) years of age, to engage in sexual intercourse, cunnilingus, fellatio or anal intercourse or the causing of penetration, to any extent and with any object, of the genital or anal openings of another, whether or not there is any emission by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The use of force or coercion that results in personal injury to the victim;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The use of force or coercion when the perpetrator is aided or abetted by one or more persons;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>In the commission of any other crime; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>When that perpetrator is in a position of authority over the minor and uses that authority to coerce the minor to submit; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>When the perpetrator is armed with a deadly weapon.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Criminal sexual penetration of a minor is a Class A offense. The Court may order such offenders to be mentally evaluated. Upon conviction, the defendant will be required to register as a convicted sex offender with the State of New Mexico and may be subject to exclusion from the Pueblo of Picuris. The Court may order such offender to pay restitution to the victim for all unreimbursed expense relating to medical and psychological treatment without limitations to time. Those expenses covered by insurance may also be ordered under restitution.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.225 was formerly codified as 4-4-98</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.230</num>
      <heading>Criminal Trespass.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of criminal trespass if that person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Unlawfully enters or remains upon posted private property without possessing written permission from the owner or person in control of the land;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Unlawfully enters or remains upon posted lands of another knowing that such consent to enter or remain is denied or withdrawn by the owner or occupant thereof;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Unlawfully enters upon the lands of another without prior permission and injures, damages, or destroys any part of the realty or its improvements, including buildings, structures, trees, shrubs, or other natural features.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Criminal trespass is a Class B offense. At the discretion of the Court, such offenders may be required to pay restitution for damages to the owner.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.230 was formerly codified as 4-4-49</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.240</num>
      <heading>Cruelty to Animals.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person is guilty of cruelty to animals if he/she purposely or knowingly:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Tortures or seriously overworks an animal; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Fails to provide necessary food, care, or shelter for an animal in his/her custody; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Abandons an animal in his/her custody; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Transports or confines an animal in a cruel manner; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Kills, injures, or administers poison to an animal without legal right to do so; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Causes one animal to fight with another.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>It is a defense to prosecution under <cite path="§4.04.240">this section</cite> that the conduct of the actor toward the animal was:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>By an accepted veterinary practice; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Directly related to a bona fide experimentation for scientific research provided that if the animal is to be destroyed, the manner employed will not be unnecessarily cruel unless directly necessary to the veterinary purpose or scientific research involved.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Cruelty to animals is a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.240 was formerly codified as 4-4-41</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.250</num>
      <heading>Curfew Violation.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A minor under the age of eighteen (18) is guilty of a curfew violation if, unless accompanied by a parent or guardian, or unless in attendance at or returning directly home from an organized school, church or tribal function, he/she is away from his/her place of residence in a public place or a private place other than the place where he/she intends to spend the night with  the permission of the owner of such place, or is in a vehicle driving about except as allowed above, after the hour of 11:00 p.m. local time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Curfew violation is a Class C offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.250 was formerly codified as 4-4-29</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.260</num>
      <heading>Custodial Interference.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of custodial interference if such person takes from the boundaries of the Pueblo of Picuris or causes to be enticed to leave the boundaries of the Pueblo of Picuris, his/her child who is less than eighteen (18) years of age with the intention of holding the child permanently or for a protracted period, knowing that he/she has no legal right to do so.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Custodial interference is a Class A offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.260 was formerly codified as 4-4-23</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.270</num>
      <heading>Damaging Public Property.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of damaging public property if that person willfully disturbs, defaces, injures, and/or destroys any public real or personal property of the Pueblo, state or federal government.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Damaging public property is a Class A offense. At the discretion of the Court, such offenders may be required to pay restitution for damages.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.270 was formerly codified as 4-4-40</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.280</num>
      <heading>Demanding or Receiving a Bribe.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of demanding or receiving a bribe if that person, being a tribal official, solicits or accepts, directly or indirectly, anything of value with the intent to have his/her decision or action on any question, matter, cause, proceeding, or appointment influenced thereby, and which by law is pending or might be brought before him/her in his/her official capacity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Demanding or receiving a bribe is a Class A offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.280 was formerly codified as 4-4-85</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.290</num>
      <heading>Desecration of Church, Religious, Cultural, Historic or Sacred Site: or Removal And/Or Destruction of Historic Artifacts.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of desecration of church, religious, cultural, historic, or sacred site; or removal and/or destruction of historic artifacts if that person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Willfully, maliciously and intentionally defaces a church, religious, cultural, historic, or sacred site or any portion thereof:</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Without proper authority removes, excavates, injures, or destroys any historic, prehistoric ruin, cave, monument or any artifact and/or antiquity.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Desecration of church, religious, cultural, historic, or sacred site; or removal and/or destruction of historic artifacts is a Class A offense. Upon conviction, the offender may be subject to permanent exclusion from the Pueblo of Picuris.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>This offense is one which subjects the offender to forfeiture of all property, including vehicles at the time of arrest.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.290 was formerly codified as 4-4-48</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.300</num>
      <heading>Disobedience to a Lawful Order.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of disobedience to a lawful order if that person willfully disobeys any command, order, subpoena, or warrant duly issued, made or given by the Court, or an officer of the law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Disobedience to a lawful order is a Class B offense. Such offenders shall be required to comply with any lawful order.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.300 was formerly codified as 4-4-80</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.310</num>
      <heading>Disorderly Conduct.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of disorderly conduct if such person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Engages in violent, abusive, indecent, profane, boisterous, unreasonably loud or otherwise disorderly conduct which tends to disturb the peace;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Maliciously disturbing, threatening, or in an abrasive rude manner, intentionally touching any dwelling or vehicle occupied by any person;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Appears in public places in an intoxicated condition and does any of the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Passes out, falls, or is found asleep in a public place or on the property of another without permission; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Bothers, disrupts or otherwise intrudes upon another person or group of persons; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>Wanders about without being able to give a reasonable account of his/her destination to a law enforcement officer; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(D)</num>
            <text>Appears or is found in an area (i.e. Kivas, Plaza, etc. set aside for religious or ceremonial activities which have been traditionally or by Order of the Tribal Council or conducting authorities set aside for use free from alcoholic beverage consumption or the presence of intoxicated persons during the period of such a religious or ceremonial activity.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Disorderly conduct is a Class C offense, unless committed under Subsection A (3) d above, then it is a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.310 was formerly codified as 4-4-27</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.320</num>
      <heading>Embezzlement.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of embezzlement if that person fraudulently embezzles or converts for his/her own use, anything of value with which he/she has been entrusted with the intent to deprive the owner thereof.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Embezzlement is a Class A offense. The Court may order such offender to pay restitution.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.320 was formerly codified as 4-4-60</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.330</num>
      <heading>Escape from Custody.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of escape from custody if that person, having been placed under lawful arrest, and/or taken into legal custody by a law enforcement officer; or lawfully committed to any detention facility, escapes or attempts to escape from or after escape evades the custody and control of a law enforcement officer or detention facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Escape from custody is a Class A offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.330 was formerly codified as 4-4-77</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.340</num>
      <heading>Extortion.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of extortion if that person communicates or transmits any threat to another by any means whatsoever with the intent to wrongfully obtain anything of value or to wrongfully compel the person threatened to do or refrain from doing any act against his/her will.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Extortion is a Class A offense. The Court may order such offender to pay restitution to the victim.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.340 was formerly codified as 4-4-61</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.350</num>
      <heading>Failure to Send Children to School.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person is guilty of failure to send children to school if, being the parent, guardian or custodian, without good cause, neglects or refuses to send such child to school.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Failure to send children to school is a Class B offense. Upon the first conviction, a fine of not less than five hundred dollars ($500.00) or more than one thousand dollars ($1000.00) may be imposed, or the parent of the student may be ordered to perform community service.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>If violations of the Compulsory School Attendance Law continue, upon the second and subsequent convictions, the parent, guardian or custodian of the student who knowingly allows the student to continue to violate the Compulsory School Attendance Law shall be guilty of a Class A offense and shall be subject to a fine of not more than one thousand dollars ($1000.00) or imprisonment for a definite term not to exceed three hundred sixty-five days (365) or both.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.350 was formerly codified as 4-4-103</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.360</num>
      <heading>Failure to Submit to Treatment for a Contagious Disease.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of failure to submit to treatment for a contagious disease if that person, knowing that he/she is infected with a sexually transmitted disease, including HIV/AIDS, active tuberculosis, or any other contagious disease and who willfully exposes another to the disease, in a place other than a medical facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Court, upon finding reasonable cause to believe that the person has any of the diseases, may order the person to be examined. If, upon examination, the person is found to be infected with a contagious disease, the Court may order the person to submit to medical treatment as prescribed by a competent medical authority.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Failure to submit to treatment for a contagious disease is a Class B offense. The Court, in its discretion, may suspend such sentence if offender agrees to medical treatment.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.360 was formerly codified as 4-4-99</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.370</num>
      <heading>False Alarms.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person is guilty of false alarms if he/she knowingly:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Cause a false fire alarm or alarm of other emergency to be transmitted to or within any organization, official or volunteer, for dealing with emergencies involving danger to life or property; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Gives false information to any law enforcement officer with purpose to implicate another in an offense; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Reports to law enforcement authorities an offense or other incident within their concern knowing or believing that it did not occur; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Pretends to furnish law enforcement authorities with information relating to an offense or incident when he/she knows he/she has no information relating to such an offense or incident; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Gives a false name or address to a law enforcement officer in the lawful discharge of his/her official duties.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>False alarms are a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.370 was formerly codified as 4-4-42</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.380</num>
      <heading>False Imprisonment.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of false imprisonment if that person intentionally confines or restrains another person without his/her consent and with the knowledge that he/she has no lawful authority to do so.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>False imprisonment is a Class A offense. At the discretion of the Court, such offenders may be required to pay restitution to the victim and/or the victim's family.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.380 was formerly codified as 4-4-22</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.390</num>
      <heading>Forgery.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of forgery if that person falsely makes or alters any signature to, or any part of, any writing purporting to have any legal effect with the intent to injure or defraud another.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Forgery is a Class A offense. The Court may order such offender to pay restitution to the victim.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.390 was formerly codified as 4-4-62</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.400</num>
      <heading>Fraud.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of fraud if that person willfully misrepresents or by deceit, or by false interpretation, or by the use of false weights or measures, obtains any money or takes anything of value from another.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Fraud is a Class B offense. The Court may order such offender to pay restitution to the victim.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.400 was formerly codified as 4-4-63</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.410</num>
      <heading>Glue, Aerosol Spray; Abuse or Possession for Abuse.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of abuse or possession with intent to abuse glue and/or aerosol spray if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>That person intentionally smells, sniffs or inhales the fumes or vapors from a glue, aerosol spray product or other chemical substance for purpose of causing a condition of, or inducing, symptoms of intoxication, elation, dizziness, excitement, irrational behavior, exhilaration, or dulling of the senses, or for the purpose of in any manner changing, distorting, or disturbing the audio, visual or mental process.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>No person shall intentionally possess glue, aerosol spray product(s), and/or any other chemical substance for the illegal purpose set forth on <cite path="§4.04.410">this section</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Glue, aerosol spray; abuse or possession for abuse is a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.410 was formerly codified as 4-4-39</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.420</num>
      <heading>Harassment.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Harassment consists of knowingly pursuing a pattern of conduct that is intended to annoy, seriously alarm or terrorize another person that serves no lawful purpose. The conduct must be such that it would cause a reasonable person to suffer substantial emotional distress.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Harassment is a Class C offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.420 was formerly codified as 4-4-24</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.430</num>
      <heading>Harboring or Aiding a Criminal Offender.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of harboring or aiding a criminal offender if any person, knowingly conceals any criminal offender or gives such offender any other aid with knowledge that a criminal offender has committed a crime, with the intent that the criminal offender escape or avoid arrest, trial, conviction, or punishment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Harboring or aiding a criminal offender is a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.430 was formerly codified as 4-4-76</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.440</num>
      <heading>Impersonating a Law Enforcement Officer or Tribal Officer.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of impersonating a law enforcement officer or tribal officer if that person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Without due authority exercises or attempts to exercise the functions of any law enforcement officer or tribal officer; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Falsely assumes or pretends to be a law enforcement officer with intent to deceive another person.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Impersonating a law enforcement officer or tribal officer is a Class A offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.440 was formerly codified as 4-4-78</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.450</num>
      <heading>Improper Control of a Fire.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of improper control of a fire if that person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>By setting a fire or causing or procuring a fire to be set to any flammable vegetation or forest material, growing or being on lands of another person and without permission of the owner thereof and without proper permit issued by the Pueblo of Picuris Forest and Wildland Fire Department;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>By allowing fire to escape or spread from the control of the person having charge thereof without using reasonable and proper precaution to prevent such fire from escaping or spreading;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>By burning any flammable vegetation or forest material, whether upon his/her own land or that of another person, without using proper and reasonable precaution at all times to prevent the escape of such fire;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>By leaving any campfire burning and unattended;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>By causing a fire to be started in any flammable vegetation or forest material, growing or being upon the lands of another person, by means of any lighted cigar, cigarette, match or other manner and leaving such fire unexhausted;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Improper control of a fire is a Class A offense. The Court may order the offender to pay restitution for damages and forfeit those personal items that were used to start the fire and any other possessions that may be sold to recover costs.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.450 was formerly codified as 4-4-88</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.460</num>
      <heading>Incest.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of incest if that person knowingly intermarries or has sexual intercourse with a person within the following degrees of blood relationship:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Parents and children; including grandparents and grandchildren of every degree;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Brothers and sisters of the half, as well as of the whole blood;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Uncles and nieces/nephews; aunts and nephews/nieces.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Incest is a Class A offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.460 was formerly codified as 4-4-92</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.470</num>
      <heading>Indecent Exposure.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of indecent exposure if that person knowingly and intentionally exposes his/her primary genital area to public view.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Indecent exposure is a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.470 was formerly codified as 4-4-91</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.480</num>
      <heading>Interference with Members of Staff, Public Officials or the General Public; Trespass; or Damage to Property.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of interference with members of staff, public official or the general public; trespass; or damage to property if such person shall be in any building or facility or property owned, operated or controlled by the Pueblo, state or federal government, willfully deny to staff, public officials or the general public:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Lawful freedom of movement within the building or facility or the land on which it is situated;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Lawful use of the building or facility or the land on which it is situated;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The right of lawful entry and exit to the building or facility or the land on which it is situated; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Willfully refuses or fails to leave the said property when requested to do so by a lawful custodian of the building, facility or property if the person is committing, threatens to commit or incites others to commit any act which would disrupt, impair, interfere with or obstruct the lawful mission, processes, procedures, and/or functions of the property, building or facility.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Interference with members of staff, public officials, or the general public; trespass; or damage to property is a Class C offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.480 was formerly codified as 4-4-32</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.490</num>
      <heading>Issuing a Worthless Check.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of issuing a worthless check if that person issues in exchange for anything of value, with the intent to defraud, any check, draft, or order for payment of money upon any bank or other depository, for the payment of such check, draft, or order in full upon its presentation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Issuing a worthless check is a Class B offense. The Court may order such offender to pay restitution to the victim.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.490 was formerly codified as 4-4-64</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.500</num>
      <heading>Kidnapping.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of kidnapping if that person unlawfully takes, restrains, or confines a person, by force or deception, with the intent that the victim:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Be held for ransom;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>As a hostage or shield and confined against his/her will; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Be held to service against the victim's will.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Kidnapping is a Class A offense. Upon conviction thereof, at the discretion of the Court, such offenders may be required to pay restitution to the victim and/or the victim's family.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.500 was formerly codified as 4-4-21</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.510</num>
      <heading>Larceny.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of larceny if that person takes or exercises unlawful control over movable property not his/her own, without the permission of the owner. Upon conviction thereof, shall be sentenced as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>For property valued fifty dollars ($50) or less, shall be a Class C offense.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>For property valued over fifty dollars ($50) but not more than five hundred dollars ($500), shall be a Class B offense; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>For property valued over five hundred dollars ($500), shall be a Class A offense.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Court may order such offender to pay restitution to the owner of the stolen property.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.510 was formerly codified as 4-4-55</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.520</num>
      <heading>Libel.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of libel if that person, with the intent to harm the reputation of another, willfully writes, prints, publishes, sells or circulates any falsehood or malicious statement, knowing the same to be untrue, or which exposes another to hatred, contempt, ridicule degradation or disgrace.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Libel is a Class C offense. The Court may require such offenders to make a public retraction of the written falsehood.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.520 was formerly codified as 4-4-72</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.530</num>
      <heading>Littering.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of littering if that person knowingly discards refuse:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>On public property in any manner other than by placing the refuse in a receptacle provided for the purpose by the responsible governmental authorities, or otherwise in accordance with lawful direction; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>On private property not owned or lawfully occupied or controlled by the person, except with the consent of the owner, lessee or occupant thereof.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Littering is a Class B offense. The Court may to the extent permitted by law, as a condition to suspension of any other penalty provided by law, require the offender to pick up and remove from any public place or any private property any litter deposited thereon. The Court may also require restitution for any and all damages caused by debris, from vehicles transporting substances not securely and appropriately covered which litter the environment.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.530 was formerly codified as 4-4-52</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.540</num>
      <heading>Livestock Offense.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person is guilty of livestock offense if he/she:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Knowingly or recklessly refuses or fails to mark or brand his/her livestock when such is required in the interest of livestock identification or directed by Pueblo or government officials; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Alters, obliterates, or removes a brand or mark, or misbrands or mismarks livestock with a purpose to deceive another for any reason; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Knowingly permits his/her livestock to graze or trespass on the property of another or of the Pueblo without permission to do so or in excess of permitted time or amount; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Knowingly refuses to sell, dispose, or otherwise remove sick or otherwise infectious livestock from common grazing areas or areas where there is a substantial danger of infecting other livestock; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Knowingly fails to treat or dispose of a sick animal where there is a substantial danger of infecting other animals; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Fails to dip, inoculate or otherwise treat livestock in the manner which the Tribal Council or its designated representative shall direct; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>Makes a false report of livestock owned; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(8)</num>
          <text>Purposely obstructs or interferes with a livestock roundup.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Except in cases in which the owner or person having custody of livestock is believed to be in violation of <cite path="§4.04.540">this section</cite> cannot be found after reasonable search, no conviction shall be found for Subsections (1), (2), (3), (4) or (5) set forth above, unless the owner or person having custody of the livestock involved is given forty-eight (48) hours written notice of his/her alleged violation and he/she has not, after such period of notice, remedied the alleged violation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Livestock found to be in violation of <cite path="§4.04.540">this section</cite> may be impounded at the time an arrest is made, and may be impounded without prior notice to the owner if a Court so orders upon receipt of evidence that such animals seriously threaten the property of the Tribe or another or the health of other livestock within the exterior boundaries of the Pueblo of Picuris, and that immediate action is necessary to protect such interests from serious harm. A reasonable fee for the care of such animals may be collected prior to their release.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Livestock offense is a Class C offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.540 was formerly codified as 4-4-54</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.550</num>
      <heading>Maintaining a Public Nuisance.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of maintaining a public nuisance if that person knowingly;</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Acts in such a manner to place another person in fear of their health, safety, comfort; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Interferes with the exercise and enjoyment of public rights, including the right to use public property.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Maintaining a public nuisance is a Class C offense. At the discretion of the Court, such offenders may be required to remove or correct any property posing as a danger to public safety.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.550 was formerly codified as 4-4-50</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.560</num>
      <heading>Malicious Mischief.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of malicious mischief if that person maliciously disturbs, defaces, injures, or destroys any tangible or personal property, including, but not limited to domestic animals, or vandalizes any property not belonging to that person.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Malicious mischief is a Class B offense. At the discretion of the Court, such offenders may be required to pay restitution for damages to the victim.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.560 was formerly codified as 4-4-46</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.570</num>
      <heading>Malicious Prosecution.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of malicious prosecution if that person maliciously procures or attempts to cause a criminal charge to be brought and prosecuted against an innocent person, knowing him/her to be innocent.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Malicious prosecution is a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.570 was formerly codified as 4-4-83</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.580</num>
      <heading>Mayhem.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person is guilty of mayhem if he/she unlawfully and purposely or knowingly;</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Deprives a human being of a bodily member or disables or renders it useless; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Cuts out or disables the tongue, puts out an eye, or slits the nose, ear or lip of another.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Mayhem is a Class A offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.580 was formerly codified as 4-4-1</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.590</num>
      <heading>Negligent Use of a Deadly Weapon.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of negligent use of a deadly weapon if that person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Discharges a firearm into any building or vehicle so as to knowingly endanger a person or his/her property;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Carrying a firearm while under the influence of an intoxicant or narcotic;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Endangering the safety of another by handling or using a firearm or other deadly weapon in a negligent manner; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Discharging a firearm within one hundred (100) yards of a dwelling, building or residential area.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Negligent use of a deadly weapon is a Class B offense. Exempt from <cite path="§4.04.590">this section</cite> are law enforcement officers in the lawful discharge of their duties.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.590 was formerly codified as 4-4-70</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.600</num>
      <heading>Obstruction of Reporting or Investigation of Child Abuse or Neglect.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of obstruction of reporting or investigation of child abuse or neglect if that person knowingly obstructs, prevents, delays, interferes, or intimidates another from reporting child abuse or neglect; or denies access to a law enforcement officer or child protective services social worker in the investigation of a report of child or sexual abuse.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Obstruction of reporting or investigation of child abuse or neglect is a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.600 was formerly codified as 4-4-104</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.610</num>
      <heading>Patronizing Prostitution.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of patronizing a prostitute if that person knowingly hires or offers to hire a prostitute to engage in a sexual act for hire with that person or another.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Patronizing prostitution is a Class C offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.610 was formerly codified as 4-4-90</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.620</num>
      <heading>Perjury.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of perjury if that person makes a false statement under oath or affirmation, material to the issue or matter involved in the course of any judicial, administrative, legislative, or other official proceeding, knowing such statement to be untrue.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Perjury is a Class A offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.620 was formerly codified as 4-4-81</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.630</num>
      <heading>Polluting Waters.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of polluting waters if that person knowingly and unlawfully introduces any object or substance into any body of public water causing it to be offensive or dangerous for human or animal consumption or use.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Polluting waters is a Class A offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.630 was formerly codified as 4-4-51</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.640</num>
      <heading>Possession of a Controlled Substance.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of possession of a controlled substance if that person intentionally possesses a controlled substance as defined under the Federal Controlled Substances Act, 21 § U.S.C. 801, et seq., unless the substance was obtained pursuant to a valid prescription of a medical practitioner while acting in the course of his or her professional practice.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Possession of marijuana, cannabis concentrates, cannabis extracts, or cannabis-derived products is governed by §<cite path="§4.04.660">Section 4.04.660</cite> of this Criminal Code. A person shall not be guilty of possession of marijuana for engaging in activities authorized and in conformity with a medical cannabis program duly enacted by the Pueblo of Picuris.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Possession of a controlled substance is a Class A offense. The Court may order habitual offenders to be committed for inpatient treatment for substance abuse with any available substance abuse treatment program. Nothing in <cite path="§4.04.640">this section</cite> shall be construed as including or applying to peyote or other natural occurring herbs used or possessed for religious purposes by a member of a Native American Church or by any Native American in the practice of his or her religion.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.640 was formerly codified as 4-4-37</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.650</num>
      <heading>Possession of Alcoholic Beverages by a Person Under 21 Years of Age.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of possession of alcoholic beverages by a person under 21 years of age if that person being under 21 years of age shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Possess or consume any beer, wine, ale, whiskey or any alcoholic beverage;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Misrepresents his/her age for the purpose of purchasing or obtaining any alcoholic beverage; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Appear in any public or private place while under the influence of an intoxicating beverage to any degree.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Possession of alcoholic beverage by a person under 21 years of age is a Class B offense. The Court, may order habitual offenders to be committed for in-patient treatment for alcohol abuse.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.650 was formerly codified as 4-4-35</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.660</num>
      <heading>Possession of Marijuana.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of possession of marijuana if that person possesses, plants, cultivates, manufactures, distributes, sells, trades, or gives away marijuana, cannabis concentrates, cannabis extracts, or cannabis-derived products in an amount exceeding 23 total units, where a unit is equivalent to one gram of dried usable cannabis plant material or 200 milligrams of THC for cannabis-derived products.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of possession of marijuana if that person distributes, sells, trades, or gives away marijuana, cannabis concentrates, cannabis extracts, or cannabis-derived products in any amount to a person under eighteen (18) years of age.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>A person shall not be guilty of possession of marijuana for engaging in activities authorized and in conformity with a medical cannabis program duly enacted by the Pueblo of Picuris.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Possession of Marijuana is a Class B offense. The Court may order habitual offenders to be committed for inpatient treatment for substance abuse with any available substance abuse treatment program.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.660 was formerly codified as 4-4-36</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.670</num>
      <heading>Prostitution.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of prostitution if that person knowingly engages in or offers to engage in a sexual act for hire. The sexual act means sexual intercourse, cunnilingus, fellatio, masturbation of another, and intercourse or the causing of penetration to any extent and with any object of the genital or anal opening of another person, whether or not there is any emission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Prostitution is a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.670 was formerly codified as 4-4-89</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.680</num>
      <heading>Public Affray.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of public affray if such person voluntarily or by agreement engages in any fight with another or uses any blows or violence toward another in an angry or quarrelsome manner in any public place, to the disturbance of others.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Public affray is a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.680 was formerly codified as 4-4-28</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.690</num>
      <heading>Public Intoxication.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of public intoxication if that person is found in any public place while under the influence of intoxicating liquor, narcotics, or any other drug to the degree that he/she may endanger him/herself or other persons or property; or annoy persons in his/her vicinity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Public intoxication is a Class B offense. The Court, in its discretion, shall order habitual offenders to be committed for in-patient treatment for alcohol and/or substance abuse with any available alcoholic or drug abuse treatment program.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.690 was formerly codified as 4-4-34</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.700</num>
      <heading>Receiving Stolen Property.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of receiving stolen property if that person intentionally receives, retains, or disposes of stolen property knowing that it has been stolen or believing that it has been stolen, unless the property is received, retained, or disposed of with the intent to restore it to the owner. The requisite knowledge or belief that property has been stolen is presumed in the case of a dealer who:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Is found in possession or control of property stolen from two or more persons on two (2)	separate occasions;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Acquires stolen property for a consideration which the dealer knows is far below the property's reasonable value. A dealer shall be presumed to know the fair market value of the property in which he/she deals; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Is found in possession or control of items or property stolen within one (1) year prior to the time of the incident charged pursuant to <cite path="§4.04.700">this section</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Receiving stolen property is a Class A offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.700 was formerly codified as 4-4-65</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.710</num>
      <heading>Refusal to Take an Oath or Affirmation.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of refusal to take an oath or affirmation if that person refuses, when legally called upon, to give testimony before any Court, administrative proceeding, legislative proceeding or other authority in the Pueblo of Picuris, authorized to administer oaths or affirmations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Refusal to take an oath or affirmation is a Class C offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.710 was formerly codified as 4-4-82</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.720</num>
      <heading>Refusing to Aid an Officer.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of refusing to aid an officer if that person refuses, without sufficient cause, to help a law enforcement officer in the preservation of peace when called upon by such an officer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Refusing to aid an officer is a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.720 was formerly codified as 4-4-74</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.730</num>
      <heading>Resisting, Evading or Obstructing an Officer.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of resisting, evading, or obstructing an officer if that person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Knowingly obstructs, resists or opposes any law enforcement officer or any other duly authorized person serving or attempting to serve or execute any process, any rule, order of any Court or any other judicial writ or process;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Intentionally flees, attempts to evade or evading a law enforcement officer when the person committing the act of fleeing, attempting to evade or evasion has knowledge that the officer is attempting to apprehend or arrest him/her;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Willfully refuses to bring a vehicle to a stop when given a visual or audible signal to stop, whether by hand, voice, emergency light, flashing light, siren or other signal by a uniformed officer in an appropriately marked police vehicle; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Resisting or abusing any Judge or law enforcement officer in the lawful discharge of his/her duties.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Resisting, evading or obstructing an officer is a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.730 was formerly codified as 4-4-73</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.740</num>
      <heading>Robbery.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of robbery if that person takes anything of value from the person of another or from the immediate control of another, by use or threatened use of force or violence.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Robbery is a Class A offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.740 was formerly codified as 4-4-56</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.750</num>
      <heading>Shooting at a Dwelling or Occupied Building: at or from a Motor Vehicle.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of shooting at a dwelling or occupied building if that person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Willfully discharges a firearm at a dwelling or occupied building; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Is shooting at or from a motor vehicle; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Willfully discharges a firearm at or from a motor vehicle with reckless disregard for the person of another.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Shooting at a dwelling or occupied building, at or from a motor vehicle is a Class A offense. <cite path="§4.04.750">This section</cite> shall not apply to a law enforcement officer discharging a firearm in the lawful performance of his/her duties.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.750 was formerly codified as 4-4-19</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.760</num>
      <heading>Shoplifting.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of shoplifting if that person willfully:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Takes possession of any merchandise with the intent of converting it without paying for it;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Conceals any merchandise with the intent of converting it without paying for it;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Alters any label, price tag, or marking upon any merchandise with the intent of depriving the merchant of all or some part of the value of it; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Transfers any merchandise from the container in or on which it is displayed to any other container with the intent of depriving the merchant of all or some part of the value of it.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Shoplifting is a Class C offense. The Court may order such offender to pay restitution to the merchant.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.760 was formerly codified as 4-4-59</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.770</num>
      <heading>Stalking.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Stalking consists of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>A person knowingly pursuing a pattern of conduct that would cause a reasonable person to feel frightened, intimidated, or threatened; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The alleged stalker must intend to place another person in reasonable apprehension of death, bodily harm, sexual assault, confinement or restraint; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The alleged stalker must intend to cause a reasonable person to fear for his/her safety or the safety of a household member;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>In furtherance of the stalking, the alleged stalker must commit one or more of the following acts on more than one occasion;</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Following a person, in a place other than the residence of the alleged stalker;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Placing a person under surveillance by remaining present outside that person's school, residence, workplace, or vehicle or any other place frequented by the person, other than the residence of the alleged stalker; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>Harassing a person.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Stalking is a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>As used in <cite path="§4.04.770">this section</cite>, "household member" means a spouse, former spouse, family member, including a relative, parent, present or former step-parent, present or former in-law, child or co-parent of a child, or a person with whom the victim has had a continuing personal relationship.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>In addition to any punishment provided pursuant to the provisions of <cite path="§4.04.770">this section</cite>, the Court shall order a person convicted of stalking to participate in and complete a program of professional counseling at his/her own expense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.770 was formerly codified as 4-4-25</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.780</num>
      <heading>Tampering with Evidence.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person is guilty of tampering with evidence if, believing that an official proceeding or investigation is pending or about to be instituted, he/she:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Alters, destroys conceals or removes any record, document, or thing with purpose to impair its verity or availability in such proceeding or investigation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Makes, presents or uses any record, document, or thing knowing it to be false and with a purpose to mislead a public servant who is or may be engaged in such proceeding or investigation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Tampering with evidence is a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.780 was formerly codified as 4-4-44</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.790</num>
      <heading>Tampering with Public Records.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person is guilty of tampering with public records if he/she:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Knowingly makes a false entry in, or false alteration of, any record, document or thing belonging to or received or kept by, the Tribe or government for information or record, or required by law to be kept by others for information of the Tribe or government; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Makes, presents or uses any record, document, or thing knowing it to be false, and with purpose that it be taken as a genuine part of information of records referred to in Subsection A(1) above; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Purposely and unlawfully destroys, conceals, removes or otherwise impairs the verity or availability of any such record, document or thing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Tampering with public records is a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.790 was formerly codified as 4-4-45</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.800</num>
      <heading>Tampering with Witnesses.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person is guilty of tampering with witnesses if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Believing that an official proceeding or investigation is pending or about to be instituted, he/she attempts to induce or otherwise cause a person to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Testify or inform falsely; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Withhold any testimony, information, document or thing; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>Elude legal process summoning him/her to testify or supply evidence; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(D)</num>
            <text>Absent him/herself from any proceeding or investigation to which he/she has been legally summoned.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>He/she harms another by an unlawful act in retaliation for anything done by another in his/her capacity as a witness or informant; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>He/she solicits, accepts or agrees to accept any benefit in consideration of his/her doing any of the things specified in <cite path="§4.04.800">this section</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Tampering with witnesses is a Class A offense if the actor employs force, deception, threat or offer of a valuable benefit; otherwise, tampering with witnesses is a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.800 was formerly codified as 4-4-43</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.810</num>
      <heading>Terroristic Threats.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person is guilty of terroristic threats if he/she threatens verbally or in writing to commit any offense involving violence with intent to terrorize another or place such other in fear of imminent serious bodily injury or to cause evacuation of a building, place of assembly, or place of public transportation, or otherwise to cause serious public inconvenience, or in reckless disregard of the risk of causing such terror or inconvenience.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Terroristic Threats is a Class A offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.810 was formerly codified as 4-4-2</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.820</num>
      <heading>Trafficking a Controlled Substance.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of trafficking in a controlled substance if that person manufactures, distributes, sells, trades, gives away, or possesses with intent to distribute intent to distribute any controlled substance as defined under the Federal Controlled Substances Act, 21 § U.S.C. 801, et seq., without a valid license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Planting, cultivating, manufacturing, distributing, selling, trading, or giving away marijuana, cannabis concentrates, cannabis extracts, or cannabis-derived products is governed by §<cite path="§4.04.660">Section 4.04.660</cite> of this Criminal Code. A person shall not be guilty of possession of marijuana for engaging in activities authorized and in conformity with a medical cannabis program duly enacted by the Pueblo of Picuris.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Trafficking in a controlled substance is a Class A offense. Nothing in <cite path="§4.04.820">this section</cite> shall be construed as including or applying to peyote or other natural occurring herbs manufactured, distributed, sold, traded, given away, or possessed with intent to distribute for religious purposes by a member of a Native American Church or by any Native American in the practice of his or her religion.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.820 was formerly codified as 4-4-38</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.830</num>
      <heading>Unauthorized Graffiti on Personal or Real Property.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of unauthorized graffiti on personal or real property if that person intentionally and maliciously defaces any personal or real property of another with graffiti or other inscribed material inscribed with ink, paint, spray paint, crayon, charcoal or the use of any object without the consent of the owner of such property.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Unauthorized graffiti on personal or real property is a Class B offense. At the discretion of the Court, such offenders may be required to pay restitution for damages to the victim and/or restore the property to its original state.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.830 was formerly codified as 4-4-47</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.840</num>
      <heading>Unlawful Assembly.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of unlawful assembly if such person assembles with two (2) or more person and disturbs the peace by using force or violence; or threatens to cause such disturbance using force or violence against the person or property of another and who shall make any overt act to carry out such unlawful purpose</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Unlawful assembly is a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.840 was formerly codified as 4-4-30</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.850</num>
      <heading>Unlawful Bomb Scare.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of an unlawful bomb scare if such person knowingly makes a bomb scare consisting of falsely and maliciously stating to another that a bomb or other explosive has been placed in such a position that property or persons are likely to be injured or destroyed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Unlawful bomb scare is a Class A offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.850 was formerly codified as 4-4-33</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.860</num>
      <heading>Unlawful Carrying of a Deadly Weapon.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of unlawful carrying of a deadly weapon if that person carries a concealed loaded firearm or any type of deadly weapon on his/her person or in close proximity thereto, so that the weapon is readily accessible for use.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Unlawful carrying of a deadly weapon is a Class B offense. Any person authorized by the Pueblo, State, or Federal Governments to carry a firearm shall be exempt from <cite path="§4.04.860">this section</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.860 was formerly codified as 4-4-68</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.870</num>
      <heading>Unlawful Carrying of a Firearm in Licensed Liquor Establishment.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of unlawful carrying of a firearm in a licensed liquor establishment if that person carries a loaded or unloaded firearm on any premises licensed by the Department of Alcoholic Beverage Control for the dispensing of alcoholic beverages.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Unlawful carrying of a firearm in a licensed liquor establishment is a Class B offense. Exempt from <cite path="§4.04.870">this section</cite> are law enforcement officers in the lawful discharge of their duties; the owner or operator of the license premises or their agents, including privately employed security personnel during the performance of their duties; or by a person on the area of licensed premises, primarily utilized for vehicular traffic or parking.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.870 was formerly codified as 4-4-69</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.880</num>
      <heading>Unlawful Possession of Switchblades.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of unlawful possession of a switchblade if that person has possession of any knife which has a blade which opens automatically by hand pressure applied to a button, spring or other device in the handle of the knife, or any knife having a blade which opens or falls or is ejected into position by the force of gravity or by any outward thrust or movement from the center.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Unlawful possession of switchblades is a Class C offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.880 was formerly codified as 4-4-71</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.890</num>
      <heading>Unlawful Use of a Telephone.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of unlawful use of a telephone if such person with the intent to terrify, intimidate, threaten, harass, annoy, or offend, to telephone another person and:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Uses obscene, lewd, or profane language;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Suggests any lewd, criminal, or sexual overtures;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Threatens to inflict injury or physical harm to the person or property of another;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Attempts to extort money or any other thing of value from such person;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Disturbs by repeated anonymous telephone calls the peace, quiet, or right of privacy of any other person at the place where the telephone call or calls were received;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Maliciously makes a telephone call, whether or not a conversation ensues, with the intent to annoy or disturb another; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>Disrupts the telecommunications of another.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Unlawful use of a telephone is a Class C offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.890 was formerly codified as 4-4-31</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.900</num>
      <heading>Unlawfully Permitting Livestock upon Public Highways.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of unlawfully permitting livestock upon public highways if that person, as an owner or custodian of livestock, negligently permits his/her livestock to run at large upon any part of a public highway which is fenced on both sides.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Unlawfully permitting livestock upon public highways is a Class C offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.900 was formerly codified as 4-4-53</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.910</num>
      <heading>Vehicular Homicide.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person is guilty of vehicular homicide if, while under the influence of an alcoholic beverage, intoxicating liquor, a controlled substance, or any drug, to a degree which renders the person incapable of safely driving a vehicle, he/she causes the death of another by operating a motor vehicle in a reckless, negligent, or careless manner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Any chemical test administered on a defendant with his/her consent or after his/her arrest, whether with or against his/her consent, to determine blood alcohol content, shall be admissible in accordance with the rules of evidence.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Any presumptions established to determine intoxication based on blood alcohol content shall apply to the proof of intoxication under <cite path="§4.04.910">this section</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>For purpose of <cite path="§4.04.910">this section</cite>, a motor vehicle is any self-propelled vehicle and includes, but is not limited to any automobile, truck, van, motorcycle, all-terrain vehicle, tractor or snowmobile.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Vehicular homicide is a Class A offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.910 was formerly codified as 4-4-4</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4.04.920</num>
      <heading>Weapons Offense.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A person shall be guilty of a weapons offense if:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Being addicted to any narcotic drug, or having been declared mentally incompetent, he/she owns or has in his/her possession or under his/her custody or control a dangerous weapon; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Being intoxicated or otherwise under the influence of alcoholic beverages or other intoxicating substance, drug, or medicine, he/she has a dangerous weapon in his/her possession or under his/her custody or control; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>He/she carries a loaded firearm in a vehicle on a public road without lawful authority to do so; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>He/she has on his/her person a dangerous weapon with the intent to unlawfully assault another; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>He/she discharges any kind of firearm from a motor vehicle or within a village or posted "no shooting" recreation area without lawful authority to do so; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>He/she discharges a firearm from, upon or across any public highway without lawful authority to do so; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>Being under the age of sixteen (16) years old, he/she possesses a firearm without the consent of his/her parent or guardian.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Definition:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>"Dangerous weapon" means any item that in the manner of its use or intended use is capable of causing death or serious bodily injury. In determining whether an item, object or thing not commonly known as a dangerous weapon is a dangerous weapon, the character of the instrument, object or thing, the character of the wound produced, and the manner in which the instrument, item or thing was used shall be determinative.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>"Firearms" means pistols, revolvers, rifles, shotguns, and any device that is capable of being used as a weapon because it expels a projectile by some means of force.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>A firearm or other weapon shall be deemed loaded when there is an unexpended cartridge, shell or projectile in the firing position, except in the case of pistols and revolvers, in which case they shall be deemed loaded with the unexpended cartridge, shell or projectile is in a position that the manual operation of any mechanism would cause the unexpended cartridge, shell or projectile to be fired.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Weapons offense is a Class B offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§4.04.920 was formerly codified as 4-4-66</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
</container>
