<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" containing-doc="Pueblo of Picuris Tribal Law and Order Code">
  <prefix>Title</prefix>
  <num>6</num>
  <heading>Domestc Relations</heading>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>6.01</num>
    <heading>Marriage</heading>
    <section>
      <num>6.01.010</num>
      <heading>Marriage License.</heading>
      <text>No marriage shall be performed under authority of this Code unless the parties have first obtained a marriage license from a County Clerk or other valid jurisdiction.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.01.010 was formerly codified as 6-1-1</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>6.01.020</num>
      <heading>Existing Marriages.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>All marriages performed other than as provided for in this Domestic Relations Code, which are valid under the laws of the jurisdiction where and when performed, are valid within the jurisdiction of the Pueblo of Picuris.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>All marriages performed on the Pueblo of Picuris prior to the effective date of this Code, including those perfected according to Tribal custom, are declared valid for all purposes under this Code.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.01.020 was formerly codified as 6-1-2</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>6.01.030</num>
      <heading>Persons Who May Marry.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>No marriage license shall be issued or marriage performed within the Pueblo of Picuris unless the persons to be married meet the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Individuals to be married are eighteen (18) years of age; if either individual is sixteen (16) or seventeen (17) years of age parents' permission must be obtained; if under sixteen (16) years of age an individual can be married only with a Court Order.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>At least one of the persons to be married is an enrolled member of the Pueblo of Picuris.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.01.030 was formerly codified as 6-1-3</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>6.01.040</num>
      <heading>Officiating over Marriage Ceremonies.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A marriage may be solemnized on the Pueblo of Picuris by any of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Recognized clergy or person recognized by his/her religion as having authority to marry;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>A Judge of the Tribal Court;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The Governor of the Pueblo of Picuris;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Any person recognized by New Mexico State Law as having authority to officiate over marriages.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>No marriage solemnized before any person professing to have authority to marry shall be invalid for want of such authority, if it is consummated in the belief by the parties, that the officiant had such authority and that they have been lawfully married.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.01.040 was formerly codified as 6-1-4</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>6.01.050</num>
      <heading>Marriage Ceremony.</heading>
      <text>No particular form of marriage ceremony is required, provided, however, that the persons to be married must declare in the presence of the officiant, that they take each other as husband and wife, and that he/she must thereafter declare them to be husband and wife.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.01.050 was formerly codified as 6-1-5</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>6.01.060</num>
      <heading>Void and Voidable Marriages.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Marriages between an ancestor and his/her descendant, between brothers and sisters, of the half as well as the whole blood, between and uncle and his niece or an aunt and her nephew, or between first cousins are void from the beginning, whether or not the degree of relationship is legitimate or illegitimate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Marriages between a person who is at the time of the marriage married to another person and still living are void:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Actually believed in good faith that the prior marriage had been dissolved as a result of divorce or annulment; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Actually believed, in good faith, that his/her prior spouse is deceased.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>When a marriage is contracted in good faith and in the belief that it is a valid marriage, the issue of such marriage born or conceived prior to the voiding or receiving notice of the invalidity of the marriage for any reason shall be the legitimate issue of both parties.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>If either party to a marriage is incapable as a result of some physical cause to enter into the marital state and such cause appears to be permanent, or if the consent of either party to marry was obtained by force or fraud, the marriage is voidable.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.01.060 was formerly codified as 6-1-6</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>6.02</num>
    <heading>Annulment.</heading>
    <section>
      <num>6.02.010</num>
      <heading>Grounds for Annulment.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A marriage may be annulled for any of the following causes existing at the time of marriage:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>That the party in whose behalf it is sought to have the marriage annulled, was under eighteen (18) years of age, and such marriage was contracted without the consent of his/her parents or guardian, or persons having charge of him/her, unless, after attaining the age of consent, such party cohabits with the other as husband or wife;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>That the former husband or wife of either party was living, and the marriage with such former husband or wife was then in force;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>That either party was of unsound mind, unless such party, after coming to reason, freely cohabited with the other as husband or wife;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>That the consent of either party was obtained by fraud, unless such party afterward, with full knowledge of the facts constituting the fraud, freely cohabited with the other as husband or wife;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>That the consent of either party was obtained by force, unless such party afterwards freely cohabited with the other as husband or wife; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Impotence, which continues and appears to be incurable.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.02.010 was formerly codified as 6-2-1</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>6.02.020</num>
      <heading>Action to Annul; Parties and Limitations.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>An action to obtain a decree of annulment of a marriage, for causes mentioned in the preceding Section, must be commenced within the periods and by the parties as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>For causes mentioned in <cite path="§6.02.010|(a)|(1)">Section 6.02.010(a)(1)</cite>, by the party to the marriage who was married under the age of legal consent, within two (2) years after arriving at the age of consent, or by a parent, guardian, or other person having charge of such minor, male or female, at any time before such married minor has arrived at the legal age of consent;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>For causes mentioned in <cite path="§6.02.010|(a)|(2)">Section 6.02.010(a)(2)</cite>, by either party during the life of the other, or by such former husband or wife;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>For causes mentioned in <cite path="§6.02.010|(a)|(3)">Section 6.02.010(a)(3)</cite>, by the party injured, or relative or guardian of the party of unsound mind, at any time before the death of either party;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>For causes mentioned in <cite path="§6.02.010|(a)|(4)">Section 6.02.010(a)(4)</cite>, by the party injured, within two (2) years after the discovery of the facts constituting a fraud;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>For causes mentioned in <cite path="§6.02.010|(a)|(5)">Section 6.02.010(a)(5)</cite>, by the injured party, within four (4) years after the marriage;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>For causes mentioned in <cite path="§6.02.010|(a)|(6)">Section 6.02.010(a)(6)</cite>, by the injured party, within two (2) years after the marriage.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.02.020 was formerly codified as 6-2-2</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>6.02.030</num>
      <heading>Legitimacy of Children.</heading>
      <text>When a marriage is annulled for any reason, other than for fraud in that the wife is pregnant with a child from a man other than her husband, children begotten before judgment are legitimate and succeed to the estate of both parents. The Court may at the time of granting the annulment or at any future time, make necessary orders for the custody and support of said child or children as the circumstances and surroundings of the parents may require.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.02.030 was formerly codified as 6-2-3</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>6.02.040</num>
      <heading>Conclusiveness of Judgment of Annulment.</heading>
      <text>A final judgment, annulling a marriage, rendered during the lifetime of both the parties, is conclusive evidence of the invalidity of the marriage, in every court of record. Such a judgment, rendered after the death of either party to the marriage, is conclusive only as against the parties to the action, and those claiming under them.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.02.040 was formerly codified as 6-2-4</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>6.02.050</num>
      <heading>Legal Grounds for Dissolution of Marriage.</heading>
      <text>The Pueblo of Picuris Tribal Court establishes the following grounds for dissolution of marriage:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>No-Fault: Incompatibility because of discord and conflicts of personalities such that the legitimate ends of the marital relationship have been destroyed; preventing any reasonable expectation of reconciliation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>General: Adultery; abandonment; cruel and inhumane treatment; and incompatibility.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.02.050 was formerly codified as 6-2-5</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>6.02.060</num>
      <heading>Legal Separation.</heading>
      <text>If the spouses have permanently separated and do not live together or cohabitate, either spouse may begin the proceedings for property division, child custody, support and visitation, and spousal maintenance without asking for a dissolution of the marriage. One of the spouses must be an enrolled member of the Pueblo of Picuris, lived in the State of New Mexico consecutively for the past six (6) months, and have a legal residence in the Pueblo of Picuris.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.02.060 was formerly codified as 6-2-6</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>6.03</num>
    <heading>Divorce.</heading>
    <section>
      <num>6.03.010</num>
      <heading>Divorce and Annulment Procedure.</heading>
      <text>Proceedings in divorce and annulment shall be commenced and conducted in the manner provided by law for civil cases, except as otherwise specifically provided. A final decree of divorce shall restore the parties to the status of an unmarried person.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.03.010 was formerly codified as 6-3-1</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>6.03.020</num>
      <heading>Divorce and Annulment Residency Requirement.</heading>
      <text>In order to bring an action for divorce or annulment in the Tribal Court, at least one party to the marriage must be an enrolled member of the Pueblo of Picuris and have lived within the territorial jurisdiction of the Tribal Court for at least six (6) months prior to bringing the action, except that an annulment may be granted where either party lives within the jurisdiction of the Court and the marriage was performed under authority of this Code.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.03.020 was formerly codified as 6-3-2</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>6.03.030</num>
      <heading>Legal Grounds for Dissolution of Marriage.</heading>
      <text>The Pueblo of Picuris Tribal Court established the following grounds:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>No-Fault: Incompatibility because of discord and conflicts of personalities such that the legitimate ends of the marriage relationship have been destroyed; preventing any reasonable expectation of reconciliation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>General: adultery; abandonment; cruel and inhumane treatment; and incompatibility.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.03.030 was formerly codified as 6-3-3</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>6.03.040</num>
      <heading>Simplified or Special Dissolution of Marriage Procedures.</heading>
      <text>Marital settlement agreements and contracts for separation are specifically authorized by the Pueblo of Picuris Law and Order Code and must be in writing. Any marital settlement contracts must be recorded in the Pueblo of Picuris Tribal Court.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.03.040 was formerly codified as 6-3-4</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>6.03.050</num>
      <heading>Mediation or Counseling Requirements.</heading>
      <text>Either party may petition the Court to issue an order requiring mediation and/or counseling for the parties and/or any minor children. The Court may, in its discretion, issue an Order for Mediation and/or Counseling.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.03.050 was formerly codified as 6-3-5</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>6.03.060</num>
      <heading>Property Distribution.</heading>
      <text>The Pueblo of Picuris Tribal Court has original and exclusive jurisdiction over all property located within the boundaries of the Pueblo. Each spouse retains his or her separate property acquired prior to the marriage. This is designated as separate property by a written agreement. Any gifts and/or inheritances belong to the party to whom they were given. All property, except separate property, which a spouse acquired outside of New Mexico and which would have been community property if acquired in New Mexico is considered community property provided both parties are domiciled in New Mexico at the time the Dissolution of Marriage Petition is filed. Non-Indians and non-member Indians may not receive any portion of property or land that is part of the Pueblo of Picuris.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.03.060 was formerly codified as 6-3-6</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>6.03.070</num>
      <heading>Alimony/Maintenance/Spousal Support.</heading>
      <text>Either spouse may be awarded a just and proper amount of maintenance without regard to marital fault. The factors that the Court will consider are:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Duration of marriage;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Spouse's current and future earning capacities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The good faith efforts of the spouses to maintain employment or become self-supporting;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>The needs and obligations of each spouse;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>The age and health of the spouses;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>The amount of property that each spouse owns;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>The spouses' standard of living during the marriage;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>The maintenance of medical and life insurance during the marriage;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text>The assets of the spouses; including any income-producing property, however, a spouse shall not be required to sell assets unless there are exceptional circumstances;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(j)</num>
        <text>Each spouse's liabilities;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(k)</num>
        <text>Any marital separation or settlement agreements; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(l)</num>
        <text>Any pre or postnuptial agreements.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.03.070 was formerly codified as 6-3-7</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>6.03.080</num>
      <heading>Spouse's Name.</heading>
      <text>The Court may order the restoration of a spouse's former name upon request in the Dissolution of Marriage Petition.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.03.080 was formerly codified as 6-3-8</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>6.03.090</num>
      <heading>Prenuptial/Postnuptial Agreements.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The agreement must be in writing, signed by both parties, and acknowledged by at least two witnesses and certified by a notary public. The agreement is enforceable without consideration. However, the agreement is not enforceable if one of the parties proves:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The agreement was not executed voluntarily;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The agreement was unconscionable when executed; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Before execution of the agreement, the other party was not proved a fair and reasonable disclosure of the property or financial obligations of the other party; did not voluntarily waive any right to the disclosure of the information, and/or did not have adequate knowledge of the obligations</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>If the marriage is determined to be void, the agreement is enforceable only to the extent necessary to avoid an inequitable result.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.03.090 was formerly codified as 6-3-9</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>6.03.100</num>
      <heading>Petition and Response.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Except as otherwise provided, in the dissolution of marriage action, the petition shall state the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The name and date of birth of the parties, their social security numbers and Tribal Enrollment (census) numbers, occupation, date and place of marriage and facts relating to the residence of each respective party to include mailing and physical addresses of each party. A certified copy of marriage license must accompany the petition for dissolution of marriage.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The name, date of birth, and enrollment number of each minor child of the parties; including certified copies of birth certificates, enrollment papers and Certificates of Indian Blood.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>A list of all property, individually as well as jointly owned and the location of said property; including all financial accounts, vehicles and real property.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>A statement that the marriage is irretrievably broken or that the parties agree to a dissolution of marriage.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Whether or not an action for divorce or legal separation by either of the parties was or has at any time been filed or is pending in any court. Copies of such documents must be attached to the petition.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>If the parties have entered into any written agreement regarding support, custody, visitation, and/or division of property. Copies of all documents must be submitted to the Court.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>The relief requested of the Court.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>During the pendency of action, both parties are prohibited from and may be held in contempt of court for harassing, intimidating, physically abusing, and/or imposing any restraint on the other party or any minor child or dependent person.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>During the pendency of action, the parties are expressly prohibited from and may be held in contempt of court for encumbering, concealing, damaging, destroying, transferring or otherwise disposing of property owned by either of the parties. Property may be disposed of, during the pendency of action, by either party only with the permission of the Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>During the pendency of action, the parties are prohibited from and may be held in contempt of court for doing any of the following without the written consent of the other party or by an Order of this Court.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Establishing a residence with the parties' minor child or children outside the State of New Mexico.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Removing the parties' minor child or children from the Pueblo of Picuris and the State of New Mexico;</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Either of the parties to the marriage may initiate the action. The party who initiates the action or his/her attorney or advocate must sign the petition. Both parties and their respective attorney/advocate shall sign a joint petition if both parties are jointly filing an uncontested petition.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>The summons to the opposite party must be made by registered mail, return receipt requested or proper personal service. If only one party files the petition, the respondent will have twenty (20) days, from date of service, in which to file a written response with the Court.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.03.100 was formerly codified as 6-3-10</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>6.03.110</num>
      <heading>Judgment of Divorce.</heading>
      <text>The Pueblo of Picuris Tribal Court shall grant a judgment of divorce if:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The parties have complied with all requirements of this Statute and the Court finds that the marriage is irretrievably broken. This is not required if the parties have been living separately for twelve (12) months or longer and there are no minor children.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Court has entered an Order for an approved parenting plan and child support to include visitation. Child support guidelines will follow those in current use by the State of New Mexico.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>All property is divided between the parties.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.03.110 was formerly codified as 6-3-11</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>6.03.120</num>
      <heading>Irretrievable Breakdown; Irreconcilable Differences.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>If both of the parties, by petition or sworn testimony, have stated that the marriage is irretrievably broken and/or if the parties have voluntarily resided apart for the twelve (12) consecutive months or more prior to the filing of the action, the Court after conducting a hearing, shall make an immediate finding that the marriage is irretrievably broken and grant the divorce.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>If the parties have not voluntarily resided apart for at least twelve (12) months or longer prior to the filing of the action, and if only one party has stated, under oath, that the marriage is irretrievably broken, the Court shall consider all relevant factors, including the circumstances that gave rise to the petition and that reconciliation is not possible.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>If the Court finds no reasonable prospect of reconciliation exists or is not likely to occur, it shall make a finding that the marriage is irretrievably broken; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>If the Court finds that there is reasonable prospect of reconciliation, it shall continue the matter for a minimum of thirty (30) days, but no longer than sixty (60) days, or as soon thereafter when the matter may be properly docketed on the Court's calendar. The Court, in its discretion, may order counseling for the parties and/or any minor children.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>At the final hearing, if either party states, under oath, that the marriage is irretrievably broken, the Court shall make a finding as such, and issue the Final Decree of Divorce.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.03.120 was formerly codified as 6-3-12</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>6.03.130</num>
      <heading>Actions of the Court Pending Divorce.</heading>
      <text>The Pueblo of Picuris Tribal Court may order:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The husband or wife to provide for separate maintenance of the other spouse and any minor children.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The care, custody, and control of any minor children of the marriage during pendency proceedings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The restraint of either spouse, from interfering with the safety and well-being of the custodial parent and any minor children.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>The restraint and enjoining of either spouse or both from disposing of their individually and/or jointly owned property during the pendency of the divorce proceedings.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.03.130 was formerly codified as 6-3-13</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>6.03.140</num>
      <heading>Effects of Judgment of Divorce Decree.</heading>
      <text>The Pueblo of Picuris Tribal Court may, upon petition by any relative, godparent, sponsor, or other person who has maintained a familial relationship with any of the minor children, grant reasonable visitation rights to that person if the parents have Notice of Hearing and if the Court determines that such visitation is in the best interest of the children. The Court will, as age and maturity are appropriate, consider the wishes of the children.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.03.140 was formerly codified as 6-3-14</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>6.03.150</num>
      <heading>Filing Fees.</heading>
      <text>The filing fee for a Petition for Dissolution of Marriage is $25.00. The fee must accompany the Petition for Dissolution of Marriage.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§6.03.150 was formerly codified as 6-3-15</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
</container>
